<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise tending to shew that the just and holy God, may have a hand in the unjust actions of sinfull men: and that in such a way as shall be without any impeachment of his justnesse and holinesse, or diminution of his power and providence. By Thomas Whitfield minister of the Gospel.</title>
            <author>Whitfield, Thomas, Minister of the Gospel.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 121 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96430</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W2011</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E684_34</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207076</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866148</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866148</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118412</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96430)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118412)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 105:E684[34])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise tending to shew that the just and holy God, may have a hand in the unjust actions of sinfull men: and that in such a way as shall be without any impeachment of his justnesse and holinesse, or diminution of his power and providence. By Thomas Whitfield minister of the Gospel.</title>
                  <author>Whitfield, Thomas, Minister of the Gospel.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 47, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Wright at the Kings Head in the Old-Bayley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reissue of the original with title: The extent of divine providence.</note>
                  <note>Annotations on Thomason copy: "Jan. 28 1652"; the '3' in the imprint has been crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Theodicy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118412:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TREATISE TENDING To ſhew that the Juſt and Holy God, may have a Hand in the unjuſt actions of Sinfull Men: And that in ſuch a way as ſhall be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any impeachment of his Juſtneſſe and Holineſſe, or Diminution of his Power and PROVIDENCE.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Thomas Whitfield</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Lord is juſt in all his wayes, and holy in all his workes,</hi>
                  <bibl>Pſal. 145.17.</bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>How unſearchable are his Judgements, and his wayes paſt finding out,</hi>
                  <bibl>Rom. 11.33.</bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Wright</hi> at the Kings Head in the Old-Bayley, 1653.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:118412:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:118412:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honorable <hi>Edward</hi> Lord <hi>Mountague</hi> of <hi>Boughton,</hi> a fruitfull increaſe of piety, proſperity, and all true happineſſe both here and hereafter.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Noble Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T would not a little conduce to the happineſſe of our lives, if our thoughts (which are the immediate and to oft abortive iſſue of our minds) were right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly employed and improved: then are they well imployed, when they are converſant about the moſt excellent object: when they are taken up with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of the wiſedome, power, providence, juſtice, holines, and other excellent attributes of him who is excellency it ſelfe; in the fruition of whom is our higheſt felicity: this made the ſweet Singer of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to ſay, <hi>How precious are thy thoughts to me, O God, how great is the ſumme of them? Pſa. 139.</hi> As if he had ſaid, the thoughts of thy wiſdome, and wonderfull workings of thy providence (things which before he had mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned) are of great price and worth, being things of incomprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible excellency: yea, they are as rare as precious, the minds of moſt men being ſo ſeldom taken up with them. I am bold to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to your Lordſhip this ſmall Treatiſe, that it might give you occaſion to entertain ſuch thoughts as theſe, as alſo that it might be a teſtimony of my thankefull acknowledgement of all that ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable reſpect I have received from you. Thus humbly imploring the Father of mercies, that he would farther enrich you with the true treaſure, &amp; inable you inwardly with the graces of his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit proportionably to thoſe outward endowments wherewith he hath been pleaſed to dignifie you; I reſign you to his mercy &amp; reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honors in all due obſervance and Chriſtian ſervice. <hi>Tho. Whitfield.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:118412:3"/>
            <head>The Preface.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T hath been a queſtion much controverted in all ages, how the good and holy God can have a hand in the great evils that are done in the world: <hi>Quomodo id non fieret praeter Dei voluntate quod fit contra voluntatem</hi> (as <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſpeaks) this is done <hi>miro &amp; ineffa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bili modo</hi> (as he ſaith:) this one of the myſteries and depths of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity worthy our ſearching into. Scripture expreſſions for the moſt part hold this forth by way of action; As when it is ſaid that God hardned <hi>Pharaohs</hi> heart, that he ſent <hi>Joſeph</hi> into <hi>Egypt,</hi> that he took away <hi>Jobs</hi> Cattle which were taken away by the <hi>Chaldaeans</hi> and <hi>Subaeans,</hi> and the like. <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Arminians</hi> confine this onely to a way of permiſſion without action, and calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niate our Orthodox divines, as if they made God the Author of ſin, becauſe they bring it within the compaſſe of his will and decree, and make him to have a kind of action in it. Thus <hi>Bellarmine</hi> chargeth <hi>Zunighlius, Calvin, Peter Martyr, Beza.</hi> The like impuration alſo <hi>Arminius</hi> ſeeks to faſten on Mr. <hi>Perkins.</hi> I know well that it is far beyond my ability to untie this knot as may give ſatisfaction to all; but if I may contribute any beame of light towards the clearer diſcovery of Gods manner of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding in the production of fin: If I may helpe to vindicate the innocency and Orthodoxie of our worthy Writers from the unjuſt aſperſion of their adverſaries: eſpecially, if I may in any ſort vindicate the All wiſe, and All-working providence and power of God, from that overmuch ſtreightning and diminution which hath been put upon them for the maintaining of his juſtice: If (I ſay) I may by this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe be helpefull any of theſe wayes, I ſhall attaine the end which I aime at. Whereunto I ſhall onely promiſe theſe things briefly.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That this diſcourſe is not ſo much intended for thoſe of the learned ſort (who are better able to informe theſe lines) as for ſuch ingenuous Chriſtians, who when they meet with thoſe Scriptures wherein by the ſound of the words, God ſeems to be made the proper cauſe of ſin, they ſtumble at them, and not being able to ſatisfie themſelves deſire help this way.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I ſhall deſire the indifferent Reader, that if in this diſcourſe he ſhall meet with that which may ſeem to go higher then many of our Divines have done, in making God to have an active hand in the actions of ſinfull men: he would forbeare either to reject or cenſure, till he hath weighed the ſtrength of the arguments brought to prove the thing propounded.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If I ſhall let fall any thing in this Treatiſe, which ſhall not be agreeable to cleare evidence of Scripture, and this be made appear to be ſo; I ſhall not refuſe to unſay any thing which I have ſaid, and readily to imbrace any truth though not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing with my former apprehenſions. The good Spirit of truth make us all lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of truth, and lead us into all thoſe wayes of truth which may bring us at length to the enjoying of him who is the author of truth. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118412:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Exodus, 9.12.</bibl>
                  <p>And the Lord hardned <hi>Pharaohs</hi> heart, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <div type="introduction">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a principall priviledge belonging to the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace, and a ſpeciall promiſe which God hath made unto his people, that he would <hi>take away their ſtony heart from them, and give unto them hearts of fleſh,</hi> Ezek. 36.26. that is, that he would take away the hardneſs of their hearts: How God ſhould take away the hardneſs of heart in ſome, and yet harden the hearts of others, is not eaſie to apprehend. The ſcope of this Treatiſe is to ſhew how the juſt and holy God, may have a hand in the ſinfull actions of men; and that not onely by way of permiſſion, but alſo by ſome kind of operation and working; and yet this be done without any diminution of his juſtice, or violation of his holineſſe, but ſtill he remaine to be moſt juſt in all his waies, and holy in all his works.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. Shewing what hardneſs of heart is.</head>
               <p>HArdneſs of heart may be ſaid to be an evill quality of the ſoul, which makes it in a man inſenſible of the evill which he doth, or the evill which he ſhall ſuffer; when either he hath no feeling of it, or feels it not in that meaſure which he ſhould do; then is his heart affected with hardneſs. It is mans duty to be ſenſible of the ſin which he commits, and of the ſuffering
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:118412:4"/> which will moſt certainly follow after. God hath placed in his ſoul that faculty of Conſcience for this very end and purpoſe, to give him warning and make him take notice of both theſe that he might be affected accordingly: Now when after the comitting of ſin, there are no affections of grief, ſorrow, and trouble of ſpirit ſtirring in him, when there is no feare to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſin, nor care to prevent the evill that ſin will bring, then is the heart heardned.</p>
               <p>This hardneſs of heart is either naturall, or adventitiall and acquired; the firſt of theſe we all bring with us into the world, being either altogether inſenſible of our ſpirituall miſery, by reaſon of ſin and ſuffering, or not ſo ſenſible as we ſhould be. Hence the heart of man is ſaid to be a heart of ſtone.</p>
               <p>Acquired hardneſs is that whereby the natural is increaſed and augmented; this may in ſome degree be not onely be in the worſt but in the beſt of men, which is brought to paſſe either by cuſtom in ſinning, or by ſecret judgement, or by both; of this there are divers degrees, as</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. When a man takes liberty, voluntarily and frequently to do ſuch things as he knows to be ſinfull.</item>
                  <item>2. When he doth theſe againſt the frequent perſwaſions, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitions, and cals of the word to the contrary.</item>
                  <item>3. Againſt ſuch corrections, puniſhments and judgements which God ſhall inflict upon himſelf, or he ſhall ſee inflicted upon others for the ſame, or for the like ſins.</item>
                  <item>4. When he ſhall do this againſt the ſtirrings and ſtrivings, the checks or rebukes of his own Conſcience.</item>
                  <item>5. When notwithſtanding all theſe, he ſhall take up ſtrong reſolutions and confirmed purpoſes to do as he hath done, namely to maintain his own wil againſt Gods will. Thus may wicked men harden their own hearts; and thus i'ts often ſaid of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> that he hardned his heart, and would not let the peoplegoe, when he once ſaw that the judgement was paſt.</item>
                  <item>6. When he ſhall come to be paſt all ſence and feeling of his ſin, thus the Apoſtle ſpeaks of ſome, that <hi>being paſt feeling, gave themſelves to commit all uncleanneſſe with greedineſs,</hi> Eph. 4.10.</item>
               </list>
               <p n="2">2. There may be an acquired hardneſſe by the ſecret judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God. Thus its ſaid here that the <hi>Lord hardned</hi> Pharaohs
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118412:4"/> 
                  <hi>heart:</hi> and of <hi>Sihon,</hi> that the Lord <hi>hardned his ſpirit and made it obſtinate, that he might give him into the bands of the Iſraelites,</hi> Deut. 2.30.</p>
               <p>How this is done, more ſhall be ſpoken in the due place.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. Shewing that God is not, nor cannot be the author or proper cauſe of this, or any other ſinne.</head>
               <p>BY another and proper cauſe I underſtand <hi>cauſa perſe,</hi> ſuch a cauſe as is in it ſelf, and in i'ts own nature tends to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce, ſuch or ſuch an effect, as the Sun is the proper cauſe of light and heat, the water of moiſture and the like: That God cannot thus be the cauſe of ſin, may appear upon theſe follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing grounds.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Argu.</hi> 1.</label> God is the Author of all good, and therefore he cannot be Author of evill, for out of the <hi>ſame fountaine cannot proceed ſweet water and bitter,</hi> Jam. 3.11. As the Sun cannot be the proper cauſe of light and darkneſs, no more can the Lord be of good and evill.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>2.</label> Sin is a defect, now God is all act, yea he is <hi>actus puriſſimus &amp; perfectiſſimus,</hi> the moſt pure and perfect act; therefore he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be the Author that which is a defect: for however ſinne cleaves to mens actions, as the accident to be ſubject, yet it ſelf is a meere defect in a privation of what ſhould be.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>3.</label> Sin is contrary to thoſe excellent qualities and properties which immediately flow from the nature of God is light, ſin is darkneſs, 1 <hi>Joh</hi> 1.5.6. God is purity and holineſs, Sin is pollution and filthineſs, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.21. God is righteous, yea righteouſneſs it ſelf, all ſin is unrighteouſneſs, 1 <hi>Joh</hi> 5.17. God is perfection in the higheſt degree, all ſin is imperfection: now one contrary cannot be the proper cauſe of another.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>4.</label> God is ſaid to be ſuch a God as <hi>loveth not wickedneſſe, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can evill dwell with him;</hi> yea he <hi>hates all the workers of iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> Pſal. 5.4.5. he hates them becauſe of their ſinne: now he cannot hate that which himſelf is the Author and proper cauſe of.</p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:118412:5"/>
               <p>
                  <label>5.</label> He threatens in his word that he will puniſh all ſinne and iniquity, that <hi>he wil not hold the wicked innocent,</hi> Exod. 34.7. but <hi>he wil viſit the iniquities of the Fathers upon the Children, even unto the third and fourth Generation;</hi> that the <hi>wicked ſhall not goe unpuniſhed,</hi> Prov. 11.21. <hi>they ſhall not eſcape,</hi> 1 Theſ. 5.3. Now it cannot ſtand with his juſtice to puniſh that which himſelf is the Author and proper cauſe of.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>6.</label> Sin makes a reparation between God and the ſoul, <hi>Eſay</hi> 59.2. It is an averſion of the ſoul from God: Now God can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be the Author of that which is an averſion from him, for then he ſhould deny himſelf, but <hi>he cannot lye or denye himſelfe,</hi> 1 Tim. 2.13.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>7.</label> If God could be the Author of ſin he himſelf might be ſaid to be a ſinner; if he were the Author of unrighteouſneſs, he himſelf might be ſaid to be unrighteous; to which the Apoſtle gives an abſit, as a thing blaſphemous to ſpeak or think. Is <hi>God unrighteous which puniſheth</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>God forbid: How then ſhall he judge the world?</hi> Rom. 3.5,6.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>8.</label> The Apoſtle ſaith, that he <hi>who committeth ſin, is of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil,</hi> 1 John. 3.8. and that <hi>Chriſt came into the world to diſſolve the workes of the Devil.</hi> Now Chriſt came not into the world to diſſolve the works of God, therefore ſin is none of his work.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>9.</label> If God ſhould be the Author of ſin, then the difference betwixt good and evil would be taken away, both ariſing from the ſame cauſe in the ſame manner.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>10.</label> If God ſhould be the Author of ſin, then he ſhould ſeem to diſſemble and deale deceitfully with men; becauſe he ſo often cals off, from this as a thing which he loathes and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hors, and mean while is the parent and producer of it.</p>
               <p>By all theſe grounds it appeares that God cannot be the Author and proper cauſe of ſin, though he hath ſome kind of hand in it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:118412:5"/>
               <head>CHAP. III. Shewing how God hath a hand in the ſinful actions of men.</head>
               <p>THe juſt and holy God may be ſaid to have a hand in the unjuſt actions of ſinful men divers wayes, as</p>
               <p n="1">1. By way of permiſſion, when he ſuffers them to follow the ſinful inclinations and diſpoſitions of their own wicked na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and ſo produce actions accordingly, without reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or hindring them. Thus it is ſaid, he <hi>ſuffered the Gentiles to walke in their own waies,</hi> Act. 14.16.</p>
               <p>A man may be ſaid to have a hand in that which he willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and wittily ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ers to be done when he hath power to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it: This is granted on all hands, for if God ſhould not ſuffer ſin to be, it could not be committed. God is able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain and hinder the committing of ſin if he pleaſeth, if any thing ſhould be done whether he would or not, then were he not omnipotent.</p>
               <p n="2">2. By ſuffering Satan to tempt and provoke mon to ſinne, and by his temptations to prevaile: thus it is ſaid that he did deliver all that <hi>Job</hi> had into the hans of Satan, and then Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan ſtirres up the <hi>Caldaeans</hi> and <hi>Sabaeans,</hi> to take away his Oxen and his Camels, and to kill his Servants <hi>Job</hi> 1.12,15,17. And he ſuffered Satan to enter in the heart of <hi>Judas,</hi> and to ſtir him up to betray his Maſter.</p>
               <p n="3">3. By with-drawing his grace from men, and not affording a continuall ſupply of his helpe for their ſupport and ſuſtenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that they may be preſerved from falling. Thus it is ſaid, he <hi>tooke away his ſpirit from</hi> Saul, 2 <hi>Som.</hi> 7.15. And that when the Embaſſadors of the King of <hi>Babell</hi> came to <hi>Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah,</hi> the <hi>Lord left him to trie him, that he might know all that was in his heart,</hi> 2 Chron. 22 31. The depraved nature of man is like to a ruinous houſe that his ready to fall, if it be not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinnally under-propped and upheld by ſome ſupporters; now God is not bound to yeild this ſupport to ſinful men, but he may with-draw his helping hand from them as he pleaſeth, which when he doth, then are they ready to fall.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:118412:6"/>
               <p n="4">4. God often times puniſheth one ſin with another; thus he puniſheth the abuſe of the meanes of grace with hardneſs of heart, and the abuſe of light with greater blindneſs. Thus it is ſaid of the Jews, that <hi>God gave them the ſpirit of ſlumber, eyes that they ſhould not ſee, and eares they ſhould not heare,</hi> Rom. 11.8. And of the Gentiles, that becauſe they abuſed the light of nature; and when they knew the true God by the works of Creation, yet they did not glorifie him as God, but withheld the truth in unrighteouſneſr; <hi>therefore he gave them up to vile affections to doe ſuch things which were not ſeemely,</hi> Rom 1.21,26. And in the times of the Antichriſtian Apoſtacy, becauſe men <hi>received not the love of the truth, therefore God did ſend them ſtrong deluſions to believe lyes,</hi> 2 Theſ. 2.10,11. And thus much <hi>Bellarmine</hi> himſelf grants, for ſpeaking of <hi>Abſolons</hi> inceſt, he ſaith, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bellar. de Amiſ. grat. &amp; Sta.</hi> Pect. lib. 2. c. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>Deus decitur malum illud feciſſe, non quia culpa Abſoloxis ſed qua paena Davidis erat.</hi> God is ſaid to have done it not as it was <hi>Abſolons</hi> fault, but as it was <hi>Davids</hi> puniſhment.</p>
               <p n="5">5. God may be ſaid to have a hand in the ſinful actions of the Creature, becauſe he ſo ordereth them by his providence, that he ſuffereth ſin to be committed in one kind rather then in another: thus he ſuffered <hi>Joſephs</hi> brethren rather to ſell their brother into <hi>Egypt,</hi> then to kill him: Thus Chriſt gave leave to the Devils, rather to enter into the Swine, then into men; Beſides he ſo ordereth and over ruleth the actions of the ſinfull Creature, as he makes them ſerve to good uſes and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes; yea ſome times to ends altogether differing, yea con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to what themſelves intended. Thus he made the actions of <hi>Joſephs</hi> brethen in ſelling him into <hi>Egypt</hi> for a ſlave, to be a meanes of his greater advancement: And <hi>Hamans</hi> emnity againſt <hi>Mordecay,</hi> and the Jews in getting a decree of the King for their deſtruction, to be a meanes of their greater ſafety and preferment; And the envy of the Jews againſt Chriſt, in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing him to be put to a ſhamefull and curſed death, to be a meanes and occaſion not onely of mans ſalvation, but alſo of Chriſts greater exaltation.</p>
               <p n="6">6 God hath a hand in the ſin which man commits, ſo far as he doth ſuſtain and ſupport him in all his natural motions and actions; God being the Author of nature, doth ſupport man in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118412:6"/> all, the actions of nature, and that not onely in good, but in evill actions. Sin being a defect or privation, and ſo a kinde of none entity, cleaves away to ſomething that hath being, to ſome habite, to ſome action or motion, as the ſubject wherein it is ſeated. Now all natural actions and motions are in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves goods hence the rule holds true, that <hi>malum eſt in bono tanquam in ſubjecto,</hi> evill is in good, as in the ſubject of it. All natures workes are Gods works, <hi>In him we live, and move, and have our being,</hi> Act. 17.25. This is true not onely in regard of our External, but alſo of our internal motions and actions; not onely of the body, but of the mind: As we cannot move our hand or foot, or not our thoughts, wills and affections without him.</p>
               <p>In every ſinful action, there are two things conjoyned and included: The action it ſelf, and the defect or deformity; the inordinacy, and obliquity of it: One of theſe is as it were the matter, the other the form of it, which Divines call the <hi>materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ale and formale Pacti.</hi> The former of theſe is from God, the other from the corrupt will of the Creature. It is a true rule that <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us agit inpeccato non tanquam cauſa moralis ſed tanquam cauſa na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turalis,</hi> God acts in ſin, not as a morall, but as a natural cauſe; ſo faire onely as there is natures worke in any action. All new actions are new entities and beings, and all beings are from God, who is the firſt and moſt perfect being, and from whom all other beings proceed. All natural motions and acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are creatures, and all creatures are the work of a Creator. <note place="margin">Pet. Mart. <hi>loc. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mun. loc.</hi> 14 ſect. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>Qui equid eſt, quatenus eſt, non tantum a creaturis ſed per deum pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dueitur</hi> ſaith <hi>Peter Martyr.</hi> Every thing that is, ſo far as it is, hath his production, not onely from the Creature, but from God. And ſo far as theſe actions are beings, and from God they are good. <note place="margin">Auguſtin <hi>de Fera relig.</hi> cap. 34.</note> 
                  <hi>Ipſum quantulum cun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> eſſe bonum eſt, quia ſummun eſſe eſt ſummun bonum,</hi> ſaith Auguſtin. The very being of any thing though never ſo ſmall is good, becauſe the chiefeſt being is the chiefeſt good.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Object.</label> If it be objected that in ſins of Omiſſion there is no action, therefore in theſe God hath no hand.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſ.</label> It may be anſwered though there be no outward action yet there is an action of the minde and wil: for when a man doth omit any duty, he omits it <hi>ſciens &amp; velens,</hi> upon deliberation he
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118412:7"/> doth willingly chooſe rather to let it alone, then performe it.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pet. Mart. <hi>loc. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mun loc.</hi> 14. ſect. 20.</note> 
                  <hi>Homo corruptus vult non amare proximum, vult nonire adſaerum caelum, ac perinde videmus actum voluntatis; ille actus, quà aſtus na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarae, a Deo eſt,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Peter Martyr.</hi>) A corrupt minded man will not love his neighbour, he will not go to the holy Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies; this act of his will, ſo far as it is an act of nature, is of God.</p>
               <p>Thus we have ſeen how God hath a hand in ſin divers waies; The two firſt, are acts of his Soveraignty, whereby he acts as a fire Agem, as being bound to none. The two ſecond, are acts of his juſtice, whereby he inflicts puniſhment upon ſuch as deſerve it. The two laſt, are acts of his power and providence, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he doth not onely ſuſtaine the Creatures in their ſeverall actions and motions, but guides theſe with the ſeveral adjuncts and accidents belonging to them, to ſuch ends as ſeem beſt to his wiſdom; and in none of theſe doth he appeare in any ſort culpable.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV. Shewing that God hath a hand in the evill actions of men, more then by way of bare permiſſion.</head>
               <p>THat permiſſion is exciſed by God, in the ſinful actions of men, is by none denyed (for if he did not ſuffer them, they could not be). but whether this permiſſion be accompanied with action whether he hath any kind of efficiency or working in the evill that is done by men, is the great queſtion; the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmative part whereof may thus be proved.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Argu.</hi> 1.</label> The Scripture expreſſions whereby God is ſaid to have a hand in ſin, are almoſt alway ſuch as denote action, and not a bare permiſſion onely. It doth not ſay that God ſuffered <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh</hi> to harden his own heart, but that <hi>God hardned</hi> Pharaohs <hi>heart,</hi> Exod. 9.12. It is not ſaid that he ſuffered the <hi>Cananites</hi> to hearden their hearts againſt <hi>Joſhua;</hi> but that <hi>it was of the Lord that they ſhould harden their hearts to come againſt</hi> Iſrael, that they might deſtroy them, and they might have no favour, <hi>Joſh.</hi>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:118412:7"/> 11.20. It is not ſaid that he ſuffered <hi>Abſolon</hi> to commit wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe with his Fathers Concubins, but he tels <hi>David, What thou haſt done in ſecret I will doe in the ſight of the Sun,</hi> 2 Sam. 12.12. It is not ſaid that he ſuffered the <hi>Egyptians</hi> to hate his people, but that <hi>he turned their hearts to hate them,</hi> Pſal. 105.25. that he ſuffered the falſe Prophet to be deceived, but <hi>I the Lord have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived him,</hi> Ezek. 14 9. that he ſuffered the Gentiles to follow their vile affections, but <hi>he gave them up to vile affections,</hi> Rom 2.26. that he ſuffered thoſe who received not the love of the truth, to be led away with deluſions, but he <hi>ſhould ſend them ſtrong deluſions, to beleeve a Lye,</hi> 2 Theſ. 2.11. When our Saviour directs us to pray againſt temptation, he doth not bid us pray that God would not ſuffer us to be led into temptation, but that <hi>he would not lead us into temptation.</hi> By theſe and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places, where Gods working in ſin is held forth to us by way of action, it plainly appeares, that in the ſinfull actions of men God doth exerciſe more then a bare permiſſion: elſe why ſhould the Scripture ſo conſtantly uſe ſuch expreſſions as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>note action? The Scripture doth never ſo frequently and conſtantly ſpeake improperly in any ſubject, where it might as eaſily have ſpoken properly.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Argu.</hi> 2.</label> When God is ſaid to harden <hi>Pharaohs</hi> heart, and <hi>Pharaoh</hi> is ſaid to harden his own heart, if one of theſe may be taken by way of permiſſion only, why not the other alſo, and ſo <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh</hi> ſhould have no action in the hardning of his own heart; for though God doth act and worke in another manner then <hi>Pharaoh</hi> himſelfe doth (as ſhall more largely be ſhowne after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards) yet the ſame expreſſion being applyed to both, it plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly argues that action belongs to both in this hardning, though the manner of their acting be far different.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Argu.</hi> 3.</label> It is granted by all, that God doth permit ſin to be, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe it could not be: Now if he doth permit, then he doth <hi>volens permittere,</hi> he doth willingly permit it; for if he ſhould not willingly permit it, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n it ſhould come to paſſe againſt his will: but it cannot ſtand with his omnipotency that any thing ſhould come to paſſe whether he will or no: It is the true rule of <hi>Auſtin,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Auguſt in enchirid.</hi> cap. 95.</note> 
                  <hi>Nihil fit, niſi quod omnipotens fieri velit, vel ipſe faciendo vel permittendo ut fiat;</hi> There is nothing done but the omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118412:8"/> God will have it to be done, either by doing it himſelfe, or by permitting it to be done by others. If he willingly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits it, then he wils it, (for an act of his will paſſeth upon it) if he wills it, look how far he wils it he works it; <hi>For he is in Heaven and doth whatſoever he will,</hi> Pſal. 115.3. ſo far as he wils any thing ſhall be or come to paſſe, ſo far he acts in bringing it to paſſe; for his will is an active and operative-will. The acts of his will are <hi>actus ad intra,</hi> acts within himſelf; and all im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manent acts are of the ſame nature with himſelfe, who is <hi>totus actus,</hi> all act: how then can it be conceived that ſuch acts as theſe ſhould be without action? All theſe immanent acts, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the acts of his will, counſell, and purpoſe touching things which ſhall be as they are in him from all eternity, ſo in time he puts them forth in ſome outward action and working. Hence it is ſaid, <hi>That he workes all things according to the counſell of his will,</hi> Epheſ. 5.11.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bella mine</hi> ſaith, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bellar. de amiſs. grat. &amp; ſtatu pcti.</hi> lib. 2. c. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>Deus eſt cauſa indurationis, non poſitivè ſed nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivè ſeilicet permiſſive,</hi> God is the cauſe of hardning not poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively, but negatively; namely, by way of permiſſion, ſo that he makes permiſſion to be ſuch a thing wherein God denies and withholds all action, and thus he ſaith God hardens; But to harden is an act, and how can an act be without action, ſo that this is nothing elſe but to bring in a clear contradiction for the blinding of the truth, yea, he ſaith further, <hi>Deus praeſidet ipſis malis voluntatibvs, eas regit, gubernat, terquet, flectit, in iis inviſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liter operando;</hi> God doth as it were ſit Preſident over the evill wils of men, and doth rule, governe, wreſt and bend them by working inviſibly in them. Is not here a manifeſt contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to his negative permiſſion? for are not all theſe actions, and can there be action without action? Far more agreeable to truth is the aſſertion of Dr. <hi>Twiſſe</hi> ſpeaking of this ſubject, <note place="margin">Dr. Twiſſe <hi>vindict.</hi> l. 2 p. 27.</note> 
                  <hi>Non tantum voluiſſe Deum ab aeterno dicimus, ſed conformiter ita o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peratum eſſe in tempore, &amp; totum negotium ita adminiſtraſſe ut revera peccaret Adamus;</hi> We affirme, that God did not only will from all eternity, but did anſwerably ſo worke in time, and ſo or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the buſineſſe, that <hi>Adam</hi> ſhould certainly fall.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Argum.</hi> 4.</label> The Scripture ſaith that <hi>Herod, Pontius Pilate, and the people of Iſrael were gathered together againſt Chriſt, to do whatſoever
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118412:8"/> the hand and counſell of God had determined before to be done,</hi> Acts 4.27,28. what theſe did to Chriſt in his ſuffering was ſinfull in a high degree, yet it was done by the determinate counſel of God: and as it is in this, ſo it is in all other actions of the like na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; whatever is done in time is determined, and decreed before all time. Now the decrees of God are one<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>geticall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees, whatever he hath decreed ſhall be, he ſome way or other procures the being of it; ſo that though he be not the Author of it if it be evill, yet he hath ſome kind of efficiency and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in it: for if he ſhould leave it to others, and have no hand at all in the effecting of it, then the thing might never be, and ſo God might be diſappointed of the thing which he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed. It is a true rule being rightly underſtood, <hi>Qua decrevit fecit.</hi> If God ſhould decree to permit ſin, and that this permiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſhould be without action, without doing any thing in it, then he ſhould decree to do nothing which cannot ſtand with the nature of a decree.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Argum.</hi> 5.</label> So far as ſin makes for the glory of God, ſo far he hath a hand in effecting it (for he both decrees and workes all things which make for his glory, ſo far as they make for his glory: but ſin by accident makes much for the glory of God; The Jews crucifying and killing of Chriſt made way for the glorious worke of our redemption. The Apoſtle ſaith that mans <hi>unrighteouſneſſe commends the righteouſneſſe of God, and that the truth of God abounds through our lye, unto his glory,</hi> Rom. 3.5.7. ſo far as ſin is for God, ſo far it is from God. <hi>Of him, through him, and by him are all things, to him be honour and glory,</hi> Rom. 11. laſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Argum.</hi> 6.</label> The <hi>Subſtratum</hi> or ſubject of ſin, namely, the naturall motion or action whereto ſin cleaves, is ſuch a thing without which ſin could not be (for an accident could not be without a ſubject) men could not uſe their tongus to deceit if they could not ſpeak at all, neither could their feet be ſwift to ſhed blood if they could not go at all. But of this natural motion and acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God is the author and proper cauſe (as hath been ſhewed) if God wils to yield his concurrence to the ſubſtance of any act, it is plain that he wils that act ſhould be done, now without this act the ſin that cleaves to the act could not be; therefore he
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118412:9"/> muſt needs likewiſe ſome way both will and-work in the ſin of the act: eſpecially, becauſe in many evill actions, not onely the action it ſelf ſimply conſidered, but the pravity and defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of it, makes way, and is an occaſion whereby God gets himſelf glory.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Argu.</hi> 7.</label> If Gods permiſſion of ſin, ſhould be a bare permiſſion without action, then he ſhould be a meere ſpectator of men in their ſinfull actions, himſelf not doing any thing. And this would much diminiſh and ſtrengthen the work of his provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in ruling and governing the world, by excluding and ſhutting him out from having any working hand in the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt part of thoſe actions that are done in the world; for the number of wicked men in the world being farre greater then the number of good men, the number of evill actions, muſt needs farre exceed the number of good actions: yea thus the actions of greateſt conſequence, as the mutation or over-throw of Kingdoms, States, Common-wealths, (which for the moſt part are done in a ſinful way) ſhould be exempted, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded from the working of his providence.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Arminius</hi> ſaith, <hi>Quae deus ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> fiers vult, ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> non vult, ea per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittit:</hi> Thoſe things which God neither wils, nor wils not to be done, thoſe he permits. But is not this to make God an idle ſpectator of the greateſt part of actions that are done in the world? If a man ſtands and ſees a thing to be done, which he neither would have to be done, nor would not have to be done; wherein he will neither helpe nor hinder; doth he not here ſtand as in idle ſpectator, as one not at all caring whether the thing be done or not? and yet ſuch a kind of carriage do they attribute to God in regard of the greateſt part of things done, who make his permiſſion to be without action: yea, herein they do after a ſort contradict themſelves. For <hi>Arminius</hi> makes permiſſion to be, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Armin.</hi> in <hi>Perk.</hi> 134.</note> 
                  <hi>efficacis impedimenti ſuſpenſio,</hi> the with-holding of an efficacious impediment, of ſuch a thing as would certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hinder the doing of a thing.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſaith, <hi>Permittere eſt, gratiam efficacem qua peccatum vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tetur negare.</hi> To permit, is to deny ſuch effectual grace, as where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſin may be avoided. But can this with-holding of an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediment, and this denyal of effectual grace be without any
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:118412:9"/> action, at leaſt without the action of Gods will? and doth he not work anſwerably to his will?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Argu.</hi> 8.</label> It is granted by the adverſary, that God doth puniſh one ſin with an other; Now is it not a ridiculous thing, to ſay that the judge permits onely puniſhment to be inflicted upon a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefactor? doth he not appoint it? and if it be not juſt, he ought not to permit it: There can be neither appointing, nor execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of judgment and puniſhment without action.</p>
               <p>By all theſe aguments it plainly appeares, that God doth exerciſe more then a bare permiſſion in the ſin which man commits.</p>
               <p>This may further be confirmed by the teſtimony of the moſt Orthodox Writers: Excellent <hi>Calvin</hi> ſaith thus, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Inſtit.</hi> lib. 1. cap. 18. Sect. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Deus indurat corda hominum non tantum permittendo ſed etiam agendo.</hi> God hardneth the hearts of men, not onely by permitting, but by acting.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Lib. 2. cap. 4. Sect. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Deus dicitur indurare reprobos corum corda vertere inclinare impel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lere. Id quale ſit, nequaquam explicatur ſi confugitur ad praeſcientiam &amp; permiſſionem.</hi> God is ſaid to harden reprobates, to turn their hearts to incline and move them. How this is done, is not ſufficiently explicated, if we fly to praeſcience and permiſſion onely.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> ſaith, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Locj. Com. loc.</hi> 13. Sect. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>Eſt permiſſio quidem ſed aliquid amplius efficacibus illis loquutionibus oſtenditur.</hi> There is indeed a permiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, but ſomething more is held forth in theſe ſtrong expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions (namely ſuch as before were mentioned.)</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Locj. com. loc. 13. Sect. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>Si minus propriè loqui velineus, Deus poterit aliquo modo dici, aut initium, aut cauſa peccati, non propria quidem, ſed ea quae removens prohibens appellatur.</hi> If we will ſpeak improperly, God may be ſaid ſome way to be either the beginning, or the cauſe of ſin: no proper cauſe indeed, but that which is called the removing of what hinders.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Piſcator</hi> ſaith, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ad Amic. coll. vorſtij.</hi> Sect. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>An vero negari potefl, illum procurare negotium cujus conſilio &amp; decreto negotium geritur?</hi> Can he be denyed to procure a buſineſs to be done, by whoſe counſell and determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation the thing is done?</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Bayne</hi> ſaith, <note place="margin">Bayne <hi>on the Lords Prayer.</hi> p 129.</note> 
                  <hi>Gods ſufferance is not to be underſtood without his action, he is a voluntary agent in the things he ſuffereth;</hi> we muſt
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118412:10"/> not <hi>think his permiſſion to be a pure permiſſion, without action.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yea, not onely our modern Divines, but that famous anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent <hi>Anguſtin</hi> himſelf gives a large ſuffrage to this truth. <note place="margin">Auguſt, <hi>in Enchirid. ad laurent.</hi> cap. 100.</note> 
                  <hi>Deus permittit</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>aut volens aut invitus, non certè invitus, quia id eſſet cum triſtitia, &amp; potentia ſe majorem haberet: ſi volens per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittit, permiſſio eſt genus quoddam voluntatis.</hi> God permits a thing either willingly, or againſt his will; if againſt his will, this would be with pain and grief to him, and then he ſhould have ſome other greater in power then himſelf; if he permits wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly, then his permiſſion is ſome kind of will.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>Sencti affliguntur ſecundum Dei voluntatem,</hi> 1 Pet. 3.17. <hi>at illi non poſſunt pati niſi alter agat. Qui unit paſſionem vult actionem, actio proficiſcitur ab agente.</hi> The Saints are afflicted according to the will of God, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.17. They cannot ſuffer unleſſe another acts; he that wils the paſſion, wils the action alſo, and action proceeds from an agent.</p>
               <p>Here by the way we may take notice how ill <hi>Bellarmine</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees with S. <hi>Auſtine</hi> in this point, for the writing of this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, and anſwering to that place, Act. 2.23. where it is ſaid that Chriſt was delivered to be crucified by the determinate councell of God. He ſaith, <note place="margin">Bellar. <hi>de Amiſ. grat. &amp; ſtatu. Pcti.</hi> lib. 2. cap. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>Saepe accidit ut actio ſit mala paſſio bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, Deus voluit paſſionem &amp; patientiam ſanctorum, non autem actio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem eorum a quibus affliguntur.</hi> But this croſſeth <hi>Auſtine,</hi> who ſaith that in the Saints ſuffering, who ſuffer according to the will of God, <hi>Qui vult paſſionem vult actionem,</hi> and it is contrary to right reaſon; for action and paſſion are one and the ſamemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, one cannot be without the other, therefore he that wils the one, muſt needs will the other alſo.</p>
               <p>Further, <hi>Auſtine</hi> ſpeaking of that place, Rom. 1.26. where God is ſaid to give men up to their vile affections: hath theſe words.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Contra. Iul. Pelag.</hi> l. 5. c. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Quid eſt quod dicit, cum deſiderijs ſuis traditi dicuntur: relicti per divinam patientiam intelligendi ſunt, non per potentiam in peccata compulſi? Quaſi non ſimul poſuit haec duo idem apoſtolus patientiam nempe &amp; potentiam,</hi> Rom. 9. What is it which he ſaith, when men are ſaid to be delivered up to their to their own affections and deſires? are they to be underſtood as left onely by the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine patience, and not put forward to ſin by the divine
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118412:10"/> power, as though the ſame Apoſtle did not joyne both theſe together, namely patience and power, Rom. 9.22. Thus we ſee that this learned Father goes as high, or rather higher in his expreſſions, touching the manner of Gods working in ſin, then thoſe of our Divines have done, who are ſo much quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel'd againſt, by <hi>Bellarmine</hi> and <hi>Arminius.</hi> I know well that moſt of our Orthodox writers do ſeldom uſe that expreſſion, that God did decree ſin, or is the cauſe of it, but only that he did decree to permit ſin: but their meaning muſt needs be, that he did decree that ſin ſhould be effected and brought about in ſuch a way and manner, and by ſuch meanes, as himſelf would not be the Author or proper cauſe of it, but onely a cauſe by ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident: For if they ſhould mean that he would have no efficiency or working in it, then they ſhould make him to exerciſe a bare permiſſion in it, and ſo to be an idle ſpectator of all the ſinful actions done in the world; which is an opinion that they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together renounce and reject, as hath been already ſhewed.</p>
               <p>Doctor <hi>Twiſse</hi> hath a paſſage where he affirmes, that though God intends the evill action which man doth, yet he intends not the evill of the action: But that is meaning his, he doth not ſo intend it, as to be the Author of it, though he hath a work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hand in it, appears by many other places in his writings; as when he ſaith, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vindic. grat.</hi> lib. 2. pag. 156</note> 
                  <hi>Cum peccatum Adae eveniebat non niſi Deo volen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te eveniehat.</hi> When it ſell out that <hi>Adam</hi> did ſin, this fell out by the will of God. <hi>Excaecare est preouldubio, Effectum dare ut quis excaecaretur.</hi> To blind, is ſo to work &amp; bring it about that a man ſhould be blinded. <note place="margin">Ibid. p. 87.</note> 
                  <hi>An quae Satanas in ſanctnm Job patravit Deo tantum permittente facta ſunt? Annon Job profitetur Deum abſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſſe quae dederat?</hi> Were thoſe things which Satan did ill againſt <hi>Job,</hi> done onely by Gods permiſſion? doth not <hi>Job</hi> profeſs that God had taken away what he gave?</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ib. p. 157.</note> 
                  <hi>Decretum permiſſiuum nihilominus eſt efficax ad fines a Deo ſibi praeſtitutos quam effectivum.</hi> The permiſſive decree is no leſs effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious for the ends fore appointed of God, then his working decree. Theſe are the words of that learned man, by which it appeares, that his meaning in the former words, is not as if he denyed that God did decree the evill actions of men at all (for here he grants a decree, and that an efficacious decree) but
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:118412:11"/> only that he doth not ſo decree the evill of an action, as to be the author or proper cauſe of it; for if he ſhould not at all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the evill of mens actions, then the evill of thoſe actions ſhould fall out beſides his intention; and then it ſhould be either beſides his knowledge, and ſo he ſhould not be omniſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, or againſt his will, and ſo he ſhould not be omnipotent.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V. Shewing more particularly the manner how the righteous God hath a hand in the unrighteous actions of ſinfull men.</head>
               <p>THat God is not the Author or proper cauſe of ſin, and yet hath ſome kind of efficiency and working in it, hath been already ſhewed: it followes now to ſhew more particularly, the manner how he worketh in producing of it. The manner of Gods working in ſinfull actions is ſecret and hidden, not eaſily to be apprehended, much leſſe to be explicated; which made <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſpeake thus of it, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Contra Juſtinum Pelag.</hi> lib. 5 cap 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Quanta eſt poena tradi paſſioni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ignominiae, ſive deſerendo, ſive alio quoque vel explicabili vel inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicabili modo, &amp;c.</hi> how great a puniſhment is to be given up to unſeemly paſſions, whether this be done by way of deſerti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or by any other explicable or inexplicable way; yet there is one way, which is not altogether above our apprehenſion, but therein we may in ſome ſort diſcerne Gods manner of working in ſinfull actions, and that is by adminiſtring occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, by preſenting ſuch objects, and offering to men ſuch things are in themſelves lawfull and good, but they make an ill uſe of them, taking occaſion by them to be ſtirred to evill in ſome kind or other.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vindic.</hi> lib. 2. p. 133.</note> 
                  <hi>Licet Deo ita ſe gerere in rerum omnium adminiſtratione ut mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam &amp; occaſionem objiciat unde homines naturaliter excitentur pro varia affectuum qualitate vel ad bonum vel ad malum</hi> ſaith <hi>Dr. Twiſſe</hi> God may ſo carry himſelfe in the adminiſtration of things, as he may offer matter and occaſion, whereby men may be exci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted either to good or evill, according to the divers qualitie
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:118412:11"/> and tempers of their affections; yea, <hi>Bellarmine</hi> himſelfe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bellar. de amiſs. gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riae &amp; ſta. pcti.</hi> l. 2. c. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>Deum immutare cor principum immittendo aliquam bonam cogitationem aut ſaltem indifferentem, ex qua tamen impediuntur a propoſito ſuo &amp; ita decipiuntur;</hi> That God doth change the mind of Princes, by putting ſome thought that is good, or at leaſt indifferent, whereby they are hindred from their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and ſo are deceived.</p>
               <p>Thus God may adminiſter occaſions of ſinning either in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly or outwardly; Inwardly by ſtirring up and ſuggeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch thoughts to their minds as are in themſelves lawfull and good, or at leaſt not evill, and yet they take occaſion by them to be led to evill.</p>
               <p>It was no ill thought for <hi>Joſephs</hi> brethren to thinke that their Father loved him better then he did them, yet this was the occaſion of their envy and hatred againſt him, <hi>Gen.</hi> 37.4. It was no ill thought for <hi>Pharaoh</hi> to think that if the Iſraelites ſhould continue to multiply and increaſe as they began, they might in time grow too ſtrong for him, and ſo depart out of his country whether he would or no; yet hence he takes occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to oppreſſe them with heavie burthens, and to give com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand for murthering their male children, <hi>Exod.</hi> 2.10.13,14. <hi>Shimei</hi> whoſe heart was full of rancor and bitterneſſe againſt <hi>David,</hi> becauſe the <hi>Kingdom</hi> was tranſlated from his tribe to the Tribe of <hi>Judah</hi> when he ſaw that <hi>David</hi> was in diſtreſſe, being driven from <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> by the conſpiracy of his ſon <hi>Abſolon,</hi> and thinking it may be) that this came upon <hi>David</hi> as a juſt judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of God for his unjuſt dealing with <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riah</hi> the Hittite, hence takes occaſion to vent his ſplene by curſing of <hi>David,</hi> the the hope of impunity likewiſe helping him forward. <hi>Jeroboam</hi> thought if the people ſhould goe up yearly to worſhip at <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> this might be a means to make them returne again to the houſe of <hi>David,</hi> this was no evill thought, yet hence he takes occaſion to ſet up the Calves at <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel,</hi> whereby he made Iſrael to ſin, 1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 12.26,28. If the Jews thought that to morrow they ſhould dye, that is, that deſtruction would ſhortly come (the Prophet having denounced it) this was no ill thought, yet hence they take occaſion inſtead of faſting to fall to feaſting; <hi>Let us eat and drink for to morrow we ſhal dye,</hi> ſay
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:118412:12"/> they, Iſai. 22.13. The Jewes thought if they ſhould let Chriſt alone all men would follow after him, this thought was not evill, but hence they take occaſion of taking counſell to kill him, <hi>Joh.</hi> 11.48. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vind.</hi> lib. 2. p. 83.</note> 
                  <hi>Deus non modo occaſiones miniſtrat ſed ad conſilia ex occaſionibus nata formanda concurrit,</hi> ſaith Dr. <hi>Twiſſe. i. e.</hi> God may adminiſter occaſions outwardly, and that both by his workes and by his word; By his workes divers wayes, as</p>
               <p n="1">1. By his works of mercy; <hi>Becauſe ſentence againſt an evill worke is not executed ſpeedily</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon</hi>) <hi>therefore the hearts of the ſons of men is fully ſet in them to doe evill,</hi> Eccleſ. 8.11. <hi>Theſe things haſt thou don</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>and I was ſilent, and thou thoughteſt that I was ſuch an one as thy ſelfe,</hi> Pſal. 50.21. When God holds his peace at wicked men, when he doth not ſpeake to them in his wrath, and vexe them in his ſore diſpleaſure, then they are ready to thinke that he likes of them well enough, and of their wayes and and courſes, ſo that we ſee Gods patience and long ſuffering is an accidentall cauſe of mans ſecurity, of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption and boldneſſe in evill wayes. <hi>Magna peccandi illece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bra impunitatis ſpes</hi> (ſaith the Orators) hope of impunity is a great allurement to iniquity. And as his patience is an occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of preſumption, ſo is bounty of forgetfulneſſe, yea, of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion againſt God. <hi>When thou haſt eaten and filled thy ſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware thou forget not the Lord thy God,</hi> Deu. 8.10,11. (ſaith <hi>Moſes</hi> to the people) <hi>Give me not riches least I be ful and deny thee,</hi> Pro. 30.9. <hi>When Jeſhurun waxed fat then be kicked,</hi> then he waxed wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton and rebellious, <hi>Deut.</hi> 13.15. and it followes, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18. <hi>Thou haſt forgotten God that formed thee?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. By workes of juſtice Thus men men oftimes take occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion by the judgements and puniſhments which God inflicts upon them for ſin, to breake out further into ſin. The Lord led his people through the wilderneſſe, and cauſed them ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to meet with want of water, other whiles want of bread, ſometimes to be aſſailed by enemies, <hi>to humble and to prove them, that he might do them good in their latter end,</hi> Deut. 8.2. But the bad ones amongſt them, hence tooke occaſion to murmur and rebell againſt him: When the Lord powres the vials of his wrath upon the followers of the Beaſt, and the adherents of Ante-Chriſt, hence they take occaſion to <hi>blaſpheme God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:118412:12"/> for their paines and ſores, and repented not of their workes,</hi> Rev. 16.10. when the King of <hi>Moab</hi> was brought to great ſtreights, by the Armies of <hi>Judab</hi> and <hi>Iſrael,</hi> (to whom the Lord had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed ſucceſſe in their expedition againſt him) 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 2.17. he takes his <hi>eldeſt ſon and ſacrifices him upon the wall, ver.</hi> 27.</p>
               <p n="3">3. By his works of providence. It was the worke of a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable providence which cauſed the Iſraelites ſo exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to multiply in <hi>Egypt,</hi> yet hence <hi>Pharaob</hi> takes occaſion to oppreſſe them and to murther their male-children. It was a worke of providence that brought <hi>David</hi> in his ſlight from <hi>Saul,</hi> to <hi>Abimelech</hi> the Prieſt for relief at ſuch a time when <hi>Doeg</hi> the Edomite was with him, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22.7. now hence he takes occaſion by his falſe ſlaunders to ſtirre up <hi>Saul</hi> to kill all the Lords Prieſts at <hi>Nob,</hi> and to make him the inſtrument, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.18. It was a worke of providence that brought <hi>David</hi> to the ſight of a woman waſhing her ſelfe in her garden, when he was walking upon the roof of his houſe in an evening; this was an occaſion to him of entertaining thoughts of unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and of putting them forth into action, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 11.2,4. there was no fault at all in offering the occaſion, but all the evil aroſe from <hi>David,</hi> for <hi>Joſeph</hi> had as ſtrong an occaſion of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to allure him to the like ſin, yet was not at all hurt by it, <hi>Gen.</hi> 39.9.</p>
               <p>It was a work of providence that brought the wiſe men that came from the Eaſt, to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to enquire after the King of the Jewes who was then borne, it was the ſpeciall command of God to direct their going home another way, and not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne againe to <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> yet <hi>Herod</hi> hence takes occaſion to murther all the male children in <hi>Bethlem,</hi> and the bordering coaſts, that were two yeares old and under, <hi>Mat.</hi> 2.16.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As God by his works adminiſters occaſion to men to breake forth into ſinne, ſo he doth the like by his word; Thus he ſent his word and command to <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> charging him to let the people of Iſrael goe, but hence <hi>Pharaoh</hi> tooke an occaſion to grow ſtubborne and rebellious, and more to har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den his heart in a reſolution not to let them goe, <hi>Exod.</hi> 5.2. <hi>I know not the Lord</hi> (ſaith he) neither will I let them go; yea, the ofner <hi>Moſes</hi> came to him with command from God for doing it, the more he ſtill hardned his heart againſt it; looke as a
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:118412:13"/> ſtrong ſtreame the more it is ſtopt the higher it riſeth (though no new water be added to it) ſo it is in this caſe; Thus the Jewes the more they were warned by the Prophet of their Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, and that they ſhould not goe downe into <hi>Egypt, Jer.</hi> 42.17. the more obſtinate and wilfull they waxed both theſe wayes, <hi>Chap.</hi> 44.16 ſo when Chriſts hearers heard that which they thought touched themſelves, it is ſaid, <hi>they were filled with with wrath, and thruſting him out of the City they led him to the edge of an hill,</hi> with purpoſe to have throwen him downe headlong, <hi>Luk.</hi> 18.27. When <hi>Stephen</hi> preached ſo excellently to the Jews, they <hi>hurſt with anger, and gnaſhed upon him with their teeth, run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning violently upon him:</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Act 7.54.57.</note> So that Chriſts and <hi>Stephens</hi> preaching was an accidentall cauſe of the wrath of theſe wicked men, as the ſtopping of a ſtreame is the cauſe of the riſing of it.</p>
               <p>Hence the Apoſtle ſpeaking of the Law, ſaith, <hi>where there is no law there is no tranſgreſſion,</hi> Rom. 4.15. <hi>&amp; that ſin took occaſion by the command, and wrought in him all manner of concupiſcence; for without the Law ſin is dead, but when the Law came ſin revived,</hi> Rom. 7.8,9. that <hi>ſin took occaſion by the command and deceived him,</hi> verſe 11. ſo that the Law quickned ſin, put life into it, and ſet it on worke, it lying as it were dead before, and not ſtirring ſo ſtrongly as it did after the comming of the Law; by all which it appeares that the Law is an accidentall cauſe of ſin. Now ſo far as the Law workes it, God workes it, the Law being his agent and inſtrument.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Queſt.</label> 
                  <hi>But here it may be asked, how can it be that the Law which in it ſelfe is holy, juſt and good, ſhould any way be the cauſe of evill?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſw.</label> This ariſeth from the contrariety that is betwixt the good and holy law of God, and mans corrupt and wicked heart. there is nothing more pure and holy then the Law of God, (it being the perfect rule of righteouſneſſe, and an exact <hi>idaea</hi> of all purity and holineſſe) there is nothing more corrupt and and impure then the wicked heart of man, it being the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of all pollution and filthineſſe, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.19. <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.9.) Now it is a true rule in Logick, <hi>Contraria juxta ſe poſita magis eluceſcunt,</hi> when contraries are placed neer together, the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieties of their natures doth more appeare and put forth it ſelfe; keep fire and water at a diſtance, and the contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eties
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:118412:13"/> of their natures doth not much ſhew it ſelfe, but bring them together, caſt water upon the fire, or put coales of fire in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the water, then they fight one with the other, and the ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger overcomes the weaker: ſo the more neer and cloſe the moſt pure and holy word of God be brought and applyed to the corrupt and rebellious will of man, the more is the innate corruption and rebellion of it irritated and ſtirred up, and the more ſtrongly doth it put forth it ſelfe. The more ſtrongly the command was preſſed upon <hi>Pharaoh</hi> touching letting the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites goe, the more ſtrongly did his rebellious will riſe up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it. This we may ſee true in the ordinary carriage of wicked men: Let a proud ſwearer, or filthy ſpeaker be rebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked for their ill language, and they will the more breake forth into abuſive ſpeech. Thus we ſee how the Law and Word of God that in its owne nature tends to reſtraine and repreſſe ſin, may accidentally provoke and put men forward to greater eagerneſſe and violence in ſinning; yea, not onely the Law but the Goſpel may by accident be an occaſion of greater evil. Thus our Saviour tels the Phariſees, that if they <hi>had been blind they had had no ſinne, but becauſe they ſaid they did ſee therefore their ſin remained,</hi> Joh. 9. laſt. if they had had no meanes of knowledge, their ſin had not been ſo great, but now the light ſhined upon them, thereby their ſin was increaſed, becauſe they ſhut their eyes againſt it. Hence likewiſe the Apoſtle ſaith, that the Goſpel was to ſome the ſavour of death, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.16. In it owne nature it did tend to life, but by accident it came to be an occaſion of death to ſuch as rejected it. Thus we ſee how God may be accidentally a cauſe of ſin, namely, by admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring occaſion, and that both inwardly and outwardly, both by his workes and by his word; and <hi>Bellarmine</hi> himſelfe is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in a manner to acknowledge thus much; for he ſaith, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bellar. de amiſs. grat. &amp; ſtatu. pcti.</hi> l. 2. c. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entia Dei aliquo modo indurat, Caeterum non dicitur excecare vel in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>durare niſi per accidens ſed ipſis homines abutentes rebus bonis ſeipſos obdurat.</hi> The patience of God doth after a ſort harden men: but yet he is not ſaid to blind or to harden but onely by accident, for when they doe abuſe good things they har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den themſelves. Here <hi>Bellarmine</hi> grants that God may bee ſaid to blind and harden men by accident, when they abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:118412:14"/> his Patience and long ſuffering take occaſion from thence to harden themſelves in ſinne.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI. Shewing, that ſuch cauſes as worke by accident, may have a true efficiency, and yet not be altogether blameleſſ, in blame-worthy actions.</head>
               <p>THat accidental cauſes may have a true efficiency, and yet not be faulty when the effect is faulty, may appear both by Reaſon and Scripture.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The rule of reaſon tels us, that whatſoever hath a <hi>vis,</hi> any power or vertue to bring forth an effect, is ſo far a cauſe of that effect; For <hi>cauſa eſt cujus vi res eſt.</hi> Now there be many things which have an efficiency in bringing forth ſuch or ſuch an effect, which yet cannot juſtly be blamed, though the effect be evill.</p>
               <p>When a man ſtands ſo neare the fire that he ſcorcheth his legges, the fire hath a true efficiency in this ſcorching; yet not the fire, but the man onely is to be blamed: for though it be the natural property of the fire to burne, yet the end why the fire was made, was to warme, not to burn thoſe that ſtand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it; and that it ſcorcheth the mans leggs, it is his owne fault, becauſe he did not ſtand further off when he might have done it: and the fire was onely an accidental cauſe of ſcorch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p>When a man weares a ſword for his defence, and he in a Melancholike or mad humour, ſhall run the Sword into his own body; here not the Sword, but the man is to be blamed, becauſe the end of wearing a Sword is the ſafety, not the hurt of the owner: and though it hath a true efficiency in hurting wounding him, yet the fault onely is his owne, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he willingly turned the Sword againſt himſelf.</p>
               <p>When a Phyſitian according to the true rules of Art, ſhall adminiſter wholeſome Phyſick to his Patient for ſuch or ſuch a diſeaſe, and this meeting with ſome hidden diſtemper or cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt humour in the body, ſhall cauſe greater pain or (it may
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:118412:14"/> be) death; yet here neither the Phyſick nor Phyſitian are to be blamed, becauſe the work of both theſe in their owne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture tended to health, and was fit to procure it.</p>
               <p>When <hi>Jaſon</hi> had his impoſtume cured by the thruſting of a Sword into his body, by the hand of his enemy, this was no thank to his enemy, who intended not his health, but his death: ſo on the contrary it is no blame to the Phyſitian that intends health, and uſeth fit meanes to procure it, though death fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows by accident.</p>
               <p>When the ſame Sun beames lights upon a Garden and a Dunghil, and raiſe a ſweet ſmell from the one, and an ill ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour from the other; neither the Sun nor the beames thereof are to be blamed, becauſe the efficacy of them did extend to both a like, but the different effect did ariſe from the difference of the matter whereon they did light.</p>
               <p>The like inſtances alſo may be brought from Scripture, when a man is hewing wood with an Axe, and the head of the Axe ſlippeth from the helve, and ſlayes the ſtander by; here nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Axe nor the man are to be blamed, though they have an efficiency in the death of the other, becauſe they are onely cauſes by accident; the ſcope of neither being to hurt the ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der by, <hi>Deut.</hi> 19.5.</p>
               <p>When King Uzziah went into the Temple of the Lord to burn Incenſe, <hi>Azariah</hi> with fourſcore other Prieſts, went in after him and withſtood him, telling him that it did <hi>not belong to him to burne incenſe to the Lord;</hi> then it is ſaid <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah was wrath,</hi> 2 Chron. 26.16,17,18,19.</p>
               <p>Here the Prieſts were cauſes of the wrath of the King, but no faulty cauſes, becauſe they did but their duty, and their inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was onely to hinder him from doing that which was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful for him to do, but not to provoke him to anger and wrath.</p>
               <p>When the Phariſees were filled with wrath againſt Chriſt, and the Jews breaſt with anger againſt <hi>Stephen,</hi> becauſe they juſtly reproved them, they were accidental cauſes of their wrath and anger, but no faulty cauſes.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtle ſaith, that the Law cauſeth wrath, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.15. It cauſeth wrath by meanes of Tranſgreſſion, (for tranſgreſſion
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:118412:15"/> onely properly cauſeth wrath) as the Law is the cauſe of wrath, ſo likewiſe is the cauſe of tranſgreſſion, namely an accidental cauſe, yet no faulty cauſe, for the proper end of the Law was neither to procure wrath, nor to procure tranſgreſſion, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be a meanes to preſerve man from both theſe, by dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting him ſo to walke as he might pleaſe God; ſo when he ſaith that the <hi>motions of ſin were by the Law,</hi> (that is, were ſtirred up by the Law) <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.5. and that <hi>ſin took occaſion by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, and wrought in him all manner of conceupiſcence,</hi> verſe 11. here ſin is ſaid to be ſtirred up by the Law, and to take occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by the Commandement of working concupiſcence, and therefore the Law hath ſome kind of efficiency in producing of ſin it is an accidentall cauſe but no faulty cauſe.</p>
               <p>As the Law is in it ſelfe holy, and juſt, and good, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.12. ſo it is good that it ſhould be brought to mans underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding by the knowledge of it, and to his will and affections by the right application of it: but the more this is done (he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing leſt to himſelfe) the more doth it irritate and ſtir up cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption in him, and his will (by reaſon of the contrariety that is in it to the holy Law of God) waxeth ſo much more ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne and rebellious as the Law is more cloſely applyed to it. When the Apoſtle ſaith, that beleevers are <hi>not under the Law,</hi> Rom. 6.14. and that they are <hi>delivered from the Law, that being dead</hi> (namely that corruption) <hi>wherein we are held,</hi> Rom. 7.6. this muſt needs be underſtood of the accidentall worke of the Law, whereby (by meanes of our corruption) it ſtirs up ſin in us; for it cannot be underſtood of the Law as it is a rule of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience (becauſe then the Law ſhould be wholly aboliſhed, to which the Apoſtle gives an <hi>abſit, do we then make the Law of none effect through faith, God forbid,</hi> Rom. 3.31.) neither can it be underſtood in this place of the condemning power of the Law: for though it be true that believers are freed from the curſe and condemnation of the Law, yet this is an effect of juſtification, and hath reference to that, whereas the ſubject of the Apoſtles diſcourſe in theſe two Chapters, where he ſpeakes of freedom from the Law (namely the ſixth and ſeventh) is altogether a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ſanctification, and he brings many arguments to prove the neceſſary connexion of theſe two together, and this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:118412:15"/> the reſt, becauſe they were not under the Law they were delivered from it; they muſt not ſuffer ſin to raigne in their mortall, becauſe they were not under the Law but un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der grace, <hi>cap.</hi> 6.14. they were delivered from the Law (luſt and concupiſcence being kild in them, <hi>chap.</hi> 7.6. How were they not under the Law? how were they delivered from it? So far as they were truly ſanctified they were no longer under the accidentall worke of the Law, whereby it had power to ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritate and ſtir up the rebellion and corruption of their natures, and ſo to cauſe ſin more to abound in them, being implanted into Chriſt and made partakers of the vertue of his death and reſurrection, <hi>their old man was crucified, and their body of ſin deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> ſo as they ſhould <hi>no longer ſerve ſin,</hi> as they did before, <hi>chap.</hi> 6.6. while they were in the fleſh the <hi>motions of ſin which were by the Law</hi> (which were ſtirred up by having the Law brought nearer to them) did <hi>worke in their members to bring forth fruit unto death;</hi> but they were delivered from the Law (from that acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentall worke of the Law) that <hi>being dead wherein they were held,</hi> (their ſinfull luſts being in part mortified) <hi>that they ſhould ſerve God in newneſſe of ſpirit, and not in the oldneſſe of the letter,</hi> chap. 7.5.6. by both which places it appeares that the Law hath power to ſtir up ſin and corruption in thoſe that are in the a ſtate of corruption that remaine as yet altogether unſanctified, and ſo it is an accidentall cauſe of ſin, yet no faulty cauſe, that remaining ſtill holy, and juſt and good.</p>
               <p>In this ſence likewiſe Chriſt ſaith of himſelfe, that <hi>be came not to ſend peace but the Sword,</hi> that he came <hi>to ſet a man at vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance againſt his Father, and the daughter againſt the Mother,</hi> Mat. 10.34,35. that he came <hi>to ſet fire on the earth,</hi> Luk. 12.49. How is this to be taken, that Chriſt came not to ſend peace but the ſword? is he not the Author and purchaſor of peace? Is he not called <hi>the Prince of Peace?</hi> Iſai. 9.6. Is it not ſaid of him that <hi>he is our peace?</hi> Epheſ. 2.14. how then doth he ſay, that he came not to ſend peace? theſe words muſt needs therefore be taken with ſimilation: he came not to ſend peace; that is, not peace onely but the ſword alſo: but eſpecially, his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming was the cauſe of peace in another manner then it was of the ſword. How did it cauſe the ſword? this coming was not
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:118412:16"/> the proper cauſe of the Sword, but the ſword (that is, wars and troubles) broke forth in the world occaſionally upon his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming: for after that Chriſt came and the Goſpel was peeached in the word; ſome there were that rejected it, others embraced and entertained it, beleived and obeyed it, and accordingly made profeſſion of Chriſt and his truth; now thoſe who did thu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> came to be hated and maligned, yea to be perſecuted, and ill intreated by the other: yea by this meanes it came to paſſe that thoſe who were joyned together by the neareſt bond of outward relation came to be divided, &amp; be carryed on with the greateſt enmity and ill affection one againſt another, ſo that the <hi>brother did deliver the brother to death, and parents their children, and children did riſe up againſt their pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ents and cauſe them to be put to death,</hi> Mat. 10 21. By which it is plaine, that Chriſt and his Goſpel had a hand in both theſe, both in ſending peace, and ſending the ſword, becauſe the ſame expreſſion is uſed in both; if there were a bare permiſſion in ſending the ſword there was permiſſion only in ſending peace: if there was efficiency and working in the one, there was ſo alſo in the other (although after another manner.) In like manner, when Chriſt ſaith, that <hi>he came to ſet fire on the earth</hi> (to ſend perſecution, and that <hi>his deſire was this fire might be kindled,</hi> Luk. 12.49. It is plaine he hath a working hand herein, for what he intends and earneſtly deſires, that he likewiſe ſome way or other effectually procures.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Object.</label> 
                  <hi>If it be asked how the ſame cauſe can bring forth contrary effects, how the ſame Chriſt and the ſame Goſpell can bring both peace and trouble?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſw.</label> The anſwer is, that though Chriſt had a ſufficiency and worke in both, yet in a far differing manner; for he is the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor and proper cauſe of peace, this he both purchaſed and prayed for, of this he is <hi>cauſa per ſe,</hi> of the other he is <hi>cauſa per accidens,</hi> an accidentall cauſe onely; the end of his comming and of cauſing his Goſpel to be preached to be preached, being not to bring trouble and perſecution, but this ariſeth from the perverſe refractory wils of wicked men, who therefore hate the light becauſe their deeds are evill. As the ſame heat of the Sun ſoftens the waxe, and hardens the clay, and the ſame light of the Sun helps a good ſight to ſee better, but hurts ſore eyes,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:118412:16"/> ſo it is in this caſe. Thus alſo it is ſaid that <hi>Chriſt is ſet</hi> or appointed <hi>for the riſing and fall of many, Lu.</hi> 2.34. Not onely for the riſing of ſome, but the fall of others; that he is <hi>the corner ſtone elect and precious be is made in head of the corner to believers, but a ſtumbling ſtone and rock of offence to thoſe that are diſobedient,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.7,8. He hath an efficiency in both theſe, for the text ſayth he is made to both, but of the one he is the author and proper cauſe, and therefore altogether faultleſſe and blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, their owne willfull unbeliefe being the proper cauſe of their ſtumbling.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII. Shewing that God may worke in the ſame blame-worthy acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons with Sathan and ſinfull men, and yet himſelfe be altogether blameleſſe.</head>
               <p>THat the holy God doth worke in the ſame action with the ſinfull creature hath been already ſhewed: Not only Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than moved <hi>David</hi> to number the people but God alſo, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.1. <hi>Jacobs</hi> ſons ſold their brother into <hi>Egypt,</hi> ſo it is ſaid, that <hi>God ſent him thither,</hi> Pſal. 10,17. when <hi>Jobs</hi> cattle were taken away by ill inſtruments, <hi>Job</hi> ſaith, <hi>the Lord tooke them away. Job</hi> 1.21.</p>
               <p>Now it followes to ſhew yet further how the Lord may be blameleſſe when he workes with the creature in the ſame blame-worthy actions. This hath been in part made plaine, by that which hath been ſhewed already, namely, that in all ſinfull actions he is onely <hi>cauſa per accidens,</hi> an accidentall cauſe, no proper cauſe, which workes out of inward princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, and according to its own nature; and this yet will more clearly appeare, if we conſider the differences that are betwixt him and the ſinfull creature in their working: though they work together in the ſame action, yet they differ in the ground in the manner, and in the end of their working.</p>
               <p n="1">1. They differ in the ground; the ground of all Gods acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons is his owne moſt holy will, his owne purpoſe and good pleaſure. <hi>He worketh all things after the counſell of his owne will,</hi>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:118412:17"/> Epheſ. 1.11. <hi>Whatſoever pleaſed the Lord, that did he in heaven and in earth,</hi> Pſal. 135.6. But evill inſtruments are guided by their owne wicked wills, and not by Gods will in their evill acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, (for they do that which is contrary to his revealed will, and his ſecret will they know not) if they do the ſame things God wils yet not becauſe he wils them, but upon other corrupt grounds, when a wicked man ſins he ſeeks to fulfill the will of the fleſh, but not at all to fulfill the will of God, <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.2. he doth that which ſeems good in his owne eyes, and not which ſeems good in Gods eyes.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They differ in manner of working; for in ſinful actions <hi>God</hi> works with evil not as a moral cauſe but as a natural cauſe onely; God no where doth counſel or command, or perſwade men to do evil, but altogether the contrary: But herein wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men follow only the dictate of their depraved judgement, the ſway of their corrupt will, the motion of their inordinate affections: or are carryed on by the counſels and perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, or examples of others that are like unto themſelves.</p>
               <p>It belongs to God (as the author of nature) to uphold the creature in all its naturall motions and actions. And he moves the creatures with a motion agreeable to their ſeverall na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; as irrationall creatures, ſo alſo Angels and men: when he moves good men they work according to their natures, when he moves bad men, they worke alſo according to their natures, and this without any iniquity or injuſtice at all in God: for he is the author and proper cauſe of the motion: of the obliquity of it he is onely an accidentall cauſe (ſaith Dr. <hi>Twiſſe.</hi>)<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vindict.</hi> l. 2 p. 86.</note> True it is that in good actions he uſeth a further moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and concourſe then he doth in other actions, for there he workes not only as the author of nature, but of grace, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by a generall influence of nature, but by an influence of ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall grace; but in all actions he workes as the ſupporter of nature, whereas wicked men worke as the abuſers of nature. <hi>Bellarmine</hi> grants, that Gods has an influx into all the actions that proceed from men, and yet that he is not the author of ſin, becauſe he hath onely a generall, no particular influx into the action wherein ſin is committed, ſuch an influx as is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different either to good or evil. But by this reaſon as he is
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:118412:17"/> not the Author of evill, ſo he ſhould not be the Author of good, and if God be the Author of nature, he muſt needs have a particular influxe into all natural actions, but into good acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons he hath a double influxe, namely, not onely a naturall, but a gracious influxe.</p>
               <p n="3">3. As they differ i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the ground and manner, ſo alſo in the end of their actings. The end of all Gods actions is himſelfe, and his owne glory, <hi>He hath made all things for his owne ſake, even the wicked for the day of evill,</hi> Prov. 16 4 for this purpoſe he ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up <hi>Pharaoh</hi> that he <hi>might ſhew his power in him, and might de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare his name through all the earth,</hi> Rom. 9.17. and for this end doth he <hi>ſuffer with long patience the veſſels of wrath prepared for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction,</hi> namely to make his power knowne, <hi>verſe</hi> 22 Now the now the end which wicked men aime at in their actions is not God and his glory, but ſome unworthy and baſe reſpects of their owne; wicked men uſually make themſelves, and the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfying of their luſts the end of their actions: they prefer their owne glory before Gods, <hi>Is not this great</hi> Babel <hi>which I have built by the might of my power, and for the honour of my Majeſty,</hi> (ſaith that proud King, <hi>Dau.</hi> 4.27. How far evill inſtruments when they worke in the ſame action together with God, doe differ from him in the ground and end of their working will yet further appeare if we ſhall look into ſome particular inſtances. When Sathan aſſayled <hi>Job</hi> with his temptation, he did it out of hatred againſt him, &amp; to drive him to diſtruſt and impatience, &amp; ſo overthrow &amp; ruine him. But God did this out of love, that thereby he might exerciſe his faith and patience, and make way for his greater advancement. When Satan mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved <hi>David</hi> to number the people, he did this out of malice a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>David</hi> and the people, and that hereby he might ſtir up the anger of God againſt them: But God did it to humble <hi>David,</hi> and to make it an occaſion of inflicting juſt puniſhment upon the people for their many miſcariages. When <hi>Joſephs</hi> brethren ſold him into <hi>Egypt,</hi> they did it out of envie and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, and that they might rid themſelves of him; but God did it out of love to <hi>Jacob</hi> and his family, that it might be an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of <hi>Joſephs</hi> preferment in <hi>Egypt,</hi> and ſo of preferring of <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob</hi> and his houſhold in the time of extreame Famine: when
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:118412:18"/> the Jewes high Prieſts and Elders, delevered up Chriſt to the Souldiers to be Crucified, they it out of envy and ill will, and that they might rid the world of him: but God did it out of love and good will to his Elect, that they might be ſaved and delivered out of their loſt condition, ſo that the ends of evill inſtruments in thoſe actions wherein they worke together with God, being altogether differing, yea ſometimes contrary to Gods ends, they may be juſtly blame-worthy, when he is alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether blameleſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Object.</label> But wicked men are blame-worthy though they propound good ends to themſelves in the bad actions they doe, how then can God be blameleſſe, when he concurs with them in the ſame actions, though his end be good?</p>
               <p n="1">1 Becauſe he differs from them not onely in the end but alſo in the ground and manner of his working.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <label>Anſw.</label> 2 There is not the ſame reaſon betwixt God and man, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Creator and the creature. Man is bound not onely to aime at a right end, but alſo to be guided by a right rule, he is bound to regulate all his actions by the holy Law of God: but though man be bound to yeeld obedience to the Law, God is not bound to do it; for he made the law not for himſelfe, but for the creature, not to put himſelfe but man under the ſubjection of it: he having no other Law but his owne moſt righteous and holy will, <hi>Who ſhall ſay to him, What doeſt thou?</hi> Job 9.12. <hi>He giveth not an account to any of his matters,</hi> cap. 33.13.</p>
               <p>If he be not to give an account to any then is he not ſubject to any Law, for whoever is ſubject to the Law muſt give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count to ſome or other, elſe the Law would be of no uſe. So that this is ſufficient to make all Gods actions good, becauſe the end is alway good (namely, himſelfe and his owne glory) If a man were free from all obligation of a Law, and onely bound to aime at the glory of God, or the good of his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in the things which be doth then if he propounded theſe theſe ends to himſelfe in all his dealings with God and men, he ſhould be free from blame, but beſides this he is obliged to live by a Law, to this law he owes ſubjection, which God doth not.</p>
               <p>But God is a Law to himſelfe.</p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:118412:18"/>
               <p>If this be ſo underſtood, as that whatever is the ground and guide of his actions, it is within himſelfe, then it is true: (for he borroweth nothing from without himſelfe, which he makes the motive and ground of any of his actions, but all proceed from his owne good will and pleaſure.) But if this be ſo taken as that whatever Gods law binds man to do, his nature binds him alſo to do the like; then it holds not, for the Law binds a man to do many things to which God is not bound: it binds man not onely not to commit ſin, but alſo to hinder it (if he hath power to hinder it:) but God is not bound to this, yea, man is bound to employ all the skill and power that he hath to hinder the committing of ſin; if it were ſo with God then there ſhould never be any ſin committed in the world, for by his omnipotent power he is able to hinder it;) beſides, if there were no ſin at all, he ſhould looſe a great part of his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, for as he is able to bring light out of darkneſſe, good out of evill, ſo he daily doth it. The Apoſtle ſaith our unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe commends the righteouſneſſe of God, and ſome ſins by accident make much for the glory of God (as before hath been ſhewed.) Beſides, the Law bindes man to doe all the good he can, to convert all his children and kindred, his friends and neighbours, if we were able to doe it; God is able to do this, but he doth it not, neither is bound to do it. God ſupporteth ſinfull men in their ſinfull actions, and ſupplyeth them with naturall ſtrength for the acting of them, as in the actions of uncleanneſſe, of drunkenneſſe and the like: but man (if he were able) were bound not to do this; ſo that we ſee, God may do many things which his Law binds men not to do, &amp; the other ſide may not do many things which by his Law men are obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to do, and therefore he is not ſubject to it as men are, he is <hi>Dominus legis, non ſubditus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>True it is, that God is ſo a Law to himſelfe that he can do nothing which is contrary to his one nature, as he cannot lye, he cannot deny himſelfe; but there are ſome things forbidden in the Law, which are not contrary to the nature of God; Thus we ſee how God may worke in the ſame actions with the ſinfull creature, and yet himſelfe be altogether blameleſſe; for look as when God gets himſelfe glory by the actions of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:118412:19"/> wicked men (as by the Jewes crucifying of Chriſt) it is no thanke to them becauſe they never intended it; ſo on the other ſide, when they abuſe his power and providence (ſupporting the ſtrength of nature euen in ſinfull actions) it is no blame to him, becauſe he being the good of nature muſt ſuſtaine nature in all her actions and motions; and becauſe that as the evill which wicked men doe is onely an accidentall cauſe of his glory, ſo the good which he affords them, and the helpe which he adminiſters in upholding their naturall ſtrength, is onely an accidentall cauſe of the evill which they commit.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII. Shewing how thoſe Scriptures are to he underſtood which by the ſound of words ſeeme to make God the author and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per cauſe of ſinne.</head>
               <p>THoſe Scriptures wherein the ſame ſinfull actions are attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted both to God and men, and ſet forth by the ſame ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions (as when God ſaid, that what <hi>David</hi> had done he would doe, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.12.) ſeem to ſound ſo as if both were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like cauſes of theſe actions; therefore it will be needfull to ſpeake ſomething that may be helpfull to weaker apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for the right underſtanding of theſe Scriptures, and for clearing of Gods holineſſe and juſtice, I ſhall inſtance onely in ſome of the principall of them, and what ſhall be held forth for the clearing of theſe may likewiſe be helpfull for giving ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to other places wherein the like expreſſions are uſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Object.</label> In that place, <hi>Exodus</hi> 9.12. which was propounded for the ſubject of this diſcourſe) it is ſaid that God hardned <hi>Phara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ohs</hi> heart, afterward it is ſaid that <hi>Pharaoh</hi> hardned his owne heart, <hi>verſe</hi> 34. Now it may be asked, ſince the ſame action is attributed to both, how both were not cauſes alike in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſw.</label> The Lord did this in another way then <hi>Pharaoh</hi> did it, he did it onely by adminiſtring occaſion; he ſent Moſes with a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emptory
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:118412:19"/> emptory command to <hi>Pharaoh</hi> to let his people go; this did irritate the natural pride and rebellion of <hi>Pharaohs</hi> heart, and ſtir up in him a ſtronger and more ſtubborn reſolution not to let them go. As the command was holy, juſt and good, ſo it was good that it ſhould be applyed to <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> by propound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, and urging it upon him; but the more this was done, the worſe he grew: for the command being holy, and his heart altogether unholy; theſe two being contrary, the nearer they were brought together, the more they did ſtrive and fight one againſt another, this being the nature of contraries (as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was ſhewed.) But here was no fault at all in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, for the proper end of the command was to informe <hi>Pharaoh</hi> of his duty, and to ſtir him up to the performance of it: But <hi>Pharaoh</hi> takes a contrary courſe, for whereas the end of the command was to make him willing to let the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple goe, he takes occaſion from it to grow more refractory; either becauſe it put him in mind of the damage he ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive by their departure, (they being ſo ſerviceable in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king brick for his buildings) or that it might appear that he thought not any (no not the great God) greater then him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; and therefore he ſcorned to ſtoope and ſubmit himſelf to any of his commands. By all which it appeares, that the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand was onely an occaſion or accidentall cauſe of <hi>Pharaohs</hi> hardning, but no faulty cauſe at all. Now as the command did it, God did that being his agent, and he working by it. Neither God, nor his command, put any evill into <hi>Pharaohs</hi> heart, but by propounding good to him, and not imparting grace to perform it, he takes occaſion to become more evill. <note place="margin">Auguſtine <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 105. <hi>ad Sixtum.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Deus obdurat non impartiendo malitiam ſed non impatiendo grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am,</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Auſtine</hi>) God hardneth not by infuſing any evil, but by not beſtowing grace.</p>
               <p>To this purpoſe, Doctor <hi>Twiſs</hi> ſaith well; <note place="margin">In his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to Mr. <hi>Cotten.</hi>
                  </note> that when a man is moved to courſes contrary to his corrupt humours, whether by the word of God, or his works, theſe motions being onely by way of perſwaſion; and he doth not by grace remove or correct thoſe corrupt humours: in this caſe to move and to deny grace, is to harden. It is a good thing to move to good actions by outward perſwaſions, neither is God bound to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:118412:20"/> grace inwardly, upon all thoſe whom he doth thus per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade outwardly.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Object.</hi> 2</label> It is ſaid that God did, that which <hi>Abſolon</hi> did when he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed his Fathers Concubines.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <label>Anſw.</label> 1. As God did it, it was an Act of juſtice in puniſhing <hi>Davids</hi> ſin with <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>riahs</hi> wife, by ſuffering <hi>Abſolon</hi> to commit the like ſin with his wives.</p>
               <p n="2">2. God adminiſtred occaſion of this action, by cauſing <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> to leave his Concubins to keep his houſe: There was no evill in this, but hence <hi>Ahitophel</hi> takes occaſion to give that wicked counſell, and <hi>Abſolon</hi> takes occaſion to follow it in defiling his Fathers Concubines.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Object.</hi> 3.</label> 
                  <hi>David</hi> ſaith, that God bad <hi>Shimei</hi> go and curſe him, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.10.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſw.</label> This is not to be taken properly, as if <hi>Shimei</hi> had received a command from God to do this, but onely it ſheweth the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacy of the divine adminiſtration of things, even in ſuch things whereof God is onely a cauſe by accident.</p>
               <p n="2">2. God did adminiſter occaſion to <hi>Shimei,</hi> for his heart be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing full of rancor againſt <hi>David;</hi> he ſeeing now <hi>David</hi> to be brought into diſtreſſe, thought this a fit time to vent bis ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, becauſe now he might do it with hope of impunity (as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was ſhewed.</p>
               <p n="3">3. He did it as an Act of juſtice, <hi>David</hi> had cauſed the name of God to be blaſphemed by the ſins which he had committed, and the Lord ſuffers this wretch to curſe and blaſpheme him.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Object.</hi> 4.</label> It is ſaid that <hi>God turned the heart of the Egyptians to hate his people,</hi> Pſal. 105.25.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſw.</label> He is ſaid to doe this, not that he infuſed any hatred into their hearts, but in that he adminiſtred occaſion, for he cauſed his people to grow and increaſe exceedingly both in number and in wealth: Now this gave occaſion to the <hi>Egyptians</hi> to envy and to hate them: here the goodnes of God to his people ſtirred up evill affections in them; but this was long of their own wickedneſſe, no fault in Gods goodneſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Object.</hi> 5.</label> It is ſaid, that if the <hi>falſe Prophet be deceived, the Lord hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived him,</hi> Ezek. 14.9.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſw.</label> The deceiving of the falſe, is here attributed to God in theſe reſpects.</p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:118412:20"/>
               <p n="1">1. In that he with-drew his grace from him, and left him to the deceitfulneſs of his own heart, which was of it ſelf rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy enough to run out into wayes of error.</p>
               <p n="2">2 He did this to puniſh the people becauſe they rejected the doctrin of the true Prophets, and would not believe nor obey that truth which they held forth to them; both theſe were acts of juſtice.</p>
               <p n="3">3. By adminiſtring occaſions for the judgements threatned by the true Prophets were not preſently executed, hence the falſe Prophets took occaſion to perſwade that they ſhould never be. But further, ſometimes the true prophets did foretell a peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and flouriſhing eſtate of <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> as that <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem ſtould be called the throne of the Lord,</hi> and that <hi>all nations ſhould be gathered unto it,</hi> Jer. 3.17. <hi>That</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>ſhould be a praiſe in the earth,</hi> Eſay 62.6. <hi>That their Land ſhould no more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voure the inhabitants,</hi> Ezek. 36.14. Theſe and many other like promiſes which were not to be fulfilled till the latter dayes; the falſe Prophets underſtood and applyed to the preſent times, and ſo thereby deceived both themſelves and the people: but that they made a falſe interpretation or application of the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the true Prophes, the fault was onely in themſelves, and not in the Doctine which the other had truly taught.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Object.</hi> 6.</label> It is ſaid that God gave up the <hi>Gentiles to vile affections,</hi> Ro. 1.26. and that he ſent <hi>ſtrong deluſions to thoſe that lived under the Antichriſtian Apoſtacy,</hi> 2 Theſ. 2.2.11.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſw.</label> Theſe Gentiles had vile affections of their own, and the other wanted the love of the truth, and that God left them to their vile affections, and to the deceitfulneſs of their owne hearts, or to the deluſions of falſe Teachers; this was an act of Juſtice to puniſh the one for going againſt the light of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and, and the other for not receiving the truth in love, when it was held forth to them.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Object.</hi> 7.</label> When the evill ſpirit offered himſelf to ſeduce <hi>Ahab,</hi> the Kord bids him <hi>goe and doe it,</hi> 1 King. 22.22. Here is more then a permiſſion, here is a command; therefore here the Lord ſeemes to be Author of <hi>Ahabs</hi> being deceived by the evill ſpirit; what a man commands to be done, that he is Author and proper cauſe of.</p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:118412:21"/>
               <p n="1">
                  <label>Anſ.</label> 1. It is plaine by this Scripture, that the evill ſpirit was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to ſeduce <hi>Ahab</hi> (for he offers himſelf as an inſtrument to effect it) but that he had no power to do it without leave from God: Now when the Lord bids him go and do ſo, this hath but the force of a permiſſion, as if he had ſaid thou maiſt go and do the thing thou deſirous to do, namely to perſwade <hi>Ahab</hi> to go up to <hi>Ramoth-Gilead</hi> to battail, that he may fall there.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It may be anſwered, that all this which is here ſpoken by the prophet <hi>Michaiah,</hi> of the Lords ſitting upon a Throne, and all the hoſt of heaven appearing before him, and the queſtion and anſwer here made, that all this, (I ſay) is delivered in a parabolicall way, and therefore cannot in every breach be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken properly.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Locj. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mun. loc.</hi> 14.</note> 
                  <hi>Deus inducitur per proſopopeiam</hi> (ſaith <hi>Peter Martyr</hi>) God is brought in the perſon of a man, and ſpeaking after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of men. Now in parables, the ſcope of the parable is chiefly to be looked at, and what truth it holds forth; neither is every parabolical application to be urged as a thing really done: as in the parable of the Rich Man, he is brought in as ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>Abraham,</hi> and <hi>Abraham</hi> anſwering him again, which we cannot think was really done; ſo in this place, every circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance cannot be urged as a thing really acted, touching the Lords ſitting on a Throne, and all the hoſt of heaven ſhanding before him, and the queſtion propounded and anſwered; but this is brought in by way of reſemblance to Kings and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, who when they have buſineſs of weight in hand, are wont to conſult with their Nobles, and thoſe about them. All par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ables are ſimilitudes, and of them the rule is true, that in every ſimilitude there is <hi>aliquid diſſimile,</hi> there is ſomething that is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lide, and therefore they ought not to be ſtretched beyond their bounds, and ſo urged as if they agreed in every thing to that which they are brought to illuſtrate.</p>
               <p>Theſe are the principall Scriptuers wherein ſuch expreſſions are uſed, as ſeem to make God the Author of ſinne; for other like unto theſe, they may receive the like anſwer, namely that when God is ſaid to do the ſame things which ſinful men do, he doth it, either as the Author of nature and ſupporter of it in
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:118412:21"/> naturall actions, or as the righteous judge by withdrawing of his grace, and puniſhing one ſinne with another, or by admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtring occaſions; In all which he is altogether blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IX. Containing an anſwer to ſome objections which ariſe from that which hath been before delivered touching the manner how God hath a hand in ſinne.</head>
               <p>IT hath been ſhewed before, that God doth not onely per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſinne, but that he doth willingly permit it, therefore his will is converſant about it, and his will is more then a <hi>velleietas,</hi> a meer wiſhing, what he permits, that he wils with an active will: againſt this it may be objected.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Object.</hi> 1.</label> That will may be ſaid to be evil whoſe act is evil, that act is evill which hath an evill object (for all acts receive their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, and ſo their denomination from their object) when the act of a mans will is carryed after things unlawfull then is this act evill and ſo is the will whence it proceeds.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſw.</label> To this it may be anſwered, that ſin is not ſo wholly and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely evill, but it may have ſome reſpect of good, it may have ſome good joyned with it,</p>
               <p n="1">1. For in ſinfull acts natures worke is good (as hath been ſhewed) It is a true rule, that <hi>actus peccati in genere entis bonus eſt, in genere moris malus.</hi> The act of ſin as it is an entity, it is good, in regard of the morall affection or quantity of it, ſo it is an evill.</p>
               <p>Secondly, though in it ſelfe it be evill, yet it may be made a meanes an occaſion of good, God is able to bring good out of it. Hence <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith excellently, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Auguſt. in Enchirid.</hi> cap. 96.</note> 
                  <hi>Quamvis quae mala ſunt in quantum mala ſint, non ſin bona, tamen ut non ſolum bona, ſed eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am ſint &amp; mala bonum eſt.</hi> Although evill things ſo far as they are evill are not good, yet it is good that not only good, but evill ſhould be. Sin is in it ſelf againſt the glory of God, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he cannot will it as it is in it ſelfe, and in its owne nature,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:118412:22"/> and as wicked men will it. But as the skilfull Phyſitian can ſo order and temper ſome poyſons that though they be in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves deſtructive to nature, yet he can make them medicinall and helpfull; ſo the wiſe and mighty God is able to make that which is in it ſelfe againſt his glory, to be ſerviceable to his glory, he can worke out his owne glory from the work of mens actions, he can make them uſefull to the beſt ends; and ſo far he may both will them and worke them, namely, as he can, and will bring good out of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Enchirid.</hi> cap. 100.</note> 
                  <hi>Non ſineret bonos fieri malis, neſi omnipotens etiam de malo facere p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>t bene</hi> (ſaith <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) the good God would not ſuffer evill to be, unles he being omnipotent could bring good out of evil. To the ſame purpoſe he ſaith alſo in another place, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>De correp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es grat.</hi> cap. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>Scivit Deus magis ad omnipotentiſſimam ejus bonitatem pertinere, etiam de malis benefacere, quam mala non ſinere.</hi> God did know that it more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits his omnipotent goodneſſe to bring good out of euill, then not to ſuffe any evill at all to be; yea, <hi>Bellarmine</hi> himſelfe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth that God did <hi>Ex lapſu hominis ingens bonum elice<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e,</hi> did draw forth a wonderfull great good out of the fall of man. So that we ſee that ſin (though evill in it ſelfe, may have ſome reſpect of good in it, and ſome way make for the glory of God now in this reſpect onely, God wils it, and this he may do and his will ſtill be a juſt, holy, and righteous will.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Object.</hi> 2.</label> If mans ſin be the object of Gods decree, then mans ſins ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily (for what God hath decreed muſt neceſſarily come to paſſe) and if the decree of God be the cauſe of this neceſſitie, then likewiſe it is the cauſe of that ſin which followes upon it, and ſo God ſhall be the Author and proper cauſe of ſin.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſw.</label> That Gods decrees do not take away the liberty of mans will may appeare many wayes.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Chriſts death was decreed, for he was <hi>delivered by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terminate counſell of God,</hi> Acts. 23. yet he dyed freely, for he ſaith of himſelfe, <hi>that he laid downe his life when no man had power to take it from him,</hi> John. 10.17,18. he laid it downe willingly and freely; beſide if he had not done thus. if Chriſts death had not been voluntary, it had not been an act of perfect obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and ſo could not have been meritorious. The ſtedfaſtneſſe and firme ſtanding of the good Angels in their integrity is a
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:118412:22"/> free act, for they are not enforced to it, <note place="margin">2 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 2.13.</note> yet this was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> for they are elect Angels. The Saints are choſen to faith and ſanctification, yet they beleeve and repent freely, not being led to it by any naturall or violent neceſſity. All our natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall motions and actions proceed freely from us: yet to deny theſe to be within the compaſſe of Gods decree, were to deny a great part of his providence, <hi>In him we live and move,</hi> Act. 11.28. Pro. 16.9. And what he doth in time he hath deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined to doe before all time.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Gods decree is, <hi>actus ad intra,</hi> one of thoſe immanent acts which are alwayes within himſelfe: and of theſe acts the rule holds true, that they do <hi>nihil ponere in objecto,</hi> they put no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing into the object about which they are converſant; Gods decree alone (being an inſtrument within himſelfe) works no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing upon the creature, till it comes to execution, till ſome ſome way or other he doth put forth his purpoſe by ſome out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward act: unleſſe therfore it can be ſhewed how God in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution of his decree, by ſome outward act upon man doth ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitate mans will, his decree alone will never infer any neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie upon it, and we find the contrary by experience, namely, that we are carryed forward to the committing of ſin frely as we are to eat out meat, or drinke our drinke, or performe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other action moſt agreeable to our natures, being led to it neither by any violent or naturall neceſſity.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Gods decree is ſo far from infringing the liberty of the ſecond cauſes that it eſtabliſheth and ſtrengthens them in their liberty: for he doth not onely <hi>diſcernere rem ipſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m ſed modum rei,</hi> not onely determine and decree the thing it ſelfe, but alſo the manner of it; he determines that ſomethings ſhal come to paſſe neceſſarily, other things freely and contingently. That neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary things ſhall come to paſſe by neceſſary cauſes, contingent things by contingent cauſes. All entilies and beings as from God, with all the adjuncts and properties that belong to them, and he worketh in all things according to the nature of the things: and therefore in naturall agents he cauſeth things to come to paſſe neceſſarily, in free agents contingently: ſo that though Gods will determine mans will, yet it determines to worke contingently and freely, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t voluntas neceſſario movetur ad
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:118412:23"/> agendum ex ſuppoſitione motionis divinae, ita etiam neceſſari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> movetur ad agendum libere, quia movet Deus voluntatem hominis conveniun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſuae naturae</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> pag. 31. page 27.</note> (ſaith <hi>Dr Twiſſe</hi>) as the will is neceſſarily mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to act, upon ſuppoſition of the divine motion, ſo it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily moved to act freely, becauſe God moves mans will in a way agreeable to its owne nature. <hi>Poſito decreto neceſſe erat ut primus home peccaret, ſed neceſſe erat ut peccaret liberè.</hi> Upon ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of Gods decree it was neceſſary that the firſt man ſhould ſinne, but it was alſo neceſſary that he ſhould ſinne freely.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Cauſes by accident, never worke neceſſarily, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingently: the Sun ſends forth light neceſſarily, but darkes weake eyes contingently. The Law is onely an accidental cauſe of ſin (as before was ſhewed) and look how the law works it God workes it, and as he workes it ſo he hath decreed to worke it, therefore his decree inferres no neceſſity. Beſides a cauſe by accident never workes, till <hi>cauſa per ſe</hi> ſuch as is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly, and in its owne nature a cauſe, ſets it on worke. The Sword which a mad man weares will never move to hurt him, till he himſelfe begins to move it. The wall will never hurt the glaſſe or pot, till the drunken man or ſome other daſheth it againſt the wall: no more will the Law of God ever hurt a man till he daſheth himſelfe againſt it. Cauſes by accident are alwayes reducible to other cauſes; ſo the laſt reſolution of ſinne muſt be in the freewill of man as into the true and proper cauſe of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Object.</label> But here it may be further objected, that if that which God hath decreed doth not neceſſarily come to paſſe, then his decree may be fruſtrated.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſw.</label> This Objection makes as much againſt Gods fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, as againſt his decree, for as he cannot be diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed in his decree, ſo he cannot be deceived in his foreknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; but it is granted on all ſides, that God did foreſee and foreknow <hi>Adams</hi> fall (as all other ſins) before it was commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; and therefore his foreſight doth not hinder the free working of mans will, no more doth his decree.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It followes not that his decree may be fruſtrate and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointed, though ſome things come to paſſe contingently,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:118412:23"/> becauſe although it be neceſſary that what God hath decreed ſhould come to paſſe, yet not that it ſhould come to neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: that it ſhould be effected, <hi>Neceſſario modo &amp; neceſſarijs medijs</hi> in a neceſſary manner, and by neceſſary meanes. God having decreed that not a bone of Chriſt ſhould be broken, it was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary that this ſhould come to paſſe, and that Chriſts leggs ſhould be preſerved from breaking, when the others were bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken that were crucified with him: but yet this came not to paſſe neceſſarily, for both Chriſts bones were in their own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture <hi>fragilia, talia quae frangi poſſint,</hi> ſuch as might be broken, as alſo the Souldiers did freely abſtaine from breaking of them, without any compulſion at all.</p>
               <p>But it is not poſſible that the ſame effect ſhould come to paſſe, both neceſſarily and contingently.</p>
               <p>Yes, it is poſſible; as this effect hath reference to divers cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, as the not breaking of Chriſts bones had reference to Gods decree and appointment, it was neceſſary (as hath been ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) becauſe that could not be diſappointed; but as it had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to the ſecond cauſe, namely the free will of the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, as it was not neceſſary but contingent. So on the other ſide, the Suns giving light in the aire, and the fire burning of combuſtible matter, are neceſſary effects as they have reference to the ſecond cauſes, but contingent as they have reference to the firſt cauſe; for God doth freely, not neceſſarily concur with the Sun in his ſhining, and the fire in his burning</p>
               <p>Hence ariſe theſe diſtinctions ſo frequent with Divines, of <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſitas abſoluta &amp; hypothetica, neceſſitas cauſae &amp; conſequentiae,</hi> an abſolute and condition all neceſſity; a neceſſity of the cauſe, and of the conſequence. The abſolute neceſſity, or neceſſity of the cauſe is, when things are ſo faſt and firmely tyed together by the order of the ſecond cauſes, as according to the courſe of nature, the effect cannot come to paſſe otherwiſe then it doth: As if a man be a man, he muſt needs bea reaſonable crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; if fire be fire, it muſt needs have the property of burning; if a ſtone be a ſtone, the motion of it muſt needs tend down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. The conditionall or conſequentiall neceſſity, is when there is no ſuch faſt linking together of the ſecond cauſes, but that when they worke one way, there is a diſpoſition in them
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:118412:24"/> to worke another way, though one thing doth certainly follow another, yet by no neceſſary cauſation, but by a free and contingent manner of working. Upon ſuppoſal of Gods Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and appointment, the riſing of the Sun follows the riſing of the morning Star, and (in the Countries where we live) the comming of the warm ſummer, follows the comming in of the Swallows amongſt us, and this by a conſequentiall neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, for it is never otherwiſe, but not by any abſolute or cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall neceſſity. God having decreed and appointed concerning <hi>Eſau</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> that the elder ſhould ſerve the younger, it was neceſſary that <hi>Jacob</hi> ſhould get the birth-hood and bleſſing from his brother <hi>Eſau;</hi> but this was effected by as contingent meanes as might be: for it was no whit neceſſary that <hi>Eſau</hi> ſhould come in hungry from hunting, that <hi>Jacob</hi> ſhould have Pottage in a readineſſe, that <hi>Eſau</hi> ſhould be deſirous of them, and be willing to part with his birth-right for them; all theſe things were done freely on both parts: there was no neceſſity that <hi>Jſaac</hi> ſhould miſtake <hi>Jacob</hi> for <hi>Eſau,</hi> and his ſavory meat for <hi>Eſaus</hi> Veinſon; but all this was done moſt freely (though guided by a ſecret providence.) God having determined that the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> ſhould ſpoile the <hi>Egyptians</hi> of their Jewels, of Silver and Jewels of Gold at their departure out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> Exod 12.35. compared with Chap. 3.22. and 11.2. this muſt neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily come to paſſe; yet it was done in a moſt free manner with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any enforcement or neceſſity; for it is ſaid they asked of the <hi>Egyptians</hi> Jewels, of Silver, and Jewels of Gold, and the <hi>Lord gave them favour in their eyes, that they granted their requeſt,</hi> Chap. 12.34,35. So God having decreed the fall of <hi>Adam,</hi> it was neceſſary that this ſhould come to paſſe, but it was alſo neceſſary it ſhould come to paſſe freely: and accordingly he did freely and willingly yeild to the enticing perſwaſion of the Serpent, without any compulſion at all: For as the power of God, whereby he his able able to change the nature of things, doth not hinder the neceſſary working of neceſſary cauſes; ſo likewiſe the will of God, (whereby he hath deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined the event one way) doth not hinder the free and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingent working of contingent cauſes. Beſides every neceſſary truth, is an eternall truth; this being a moſt true rule, that
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:118412:24"/> 
                  <hi>axioma neceſſacium est quod ſemper verum eſt ne falſum eſſe potest,</hi> a neceſſary propoſition is that which is alway true, and can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be falſe, that man is a reaſonable creature, was a neceſſary truth before man was born: That a <hi>Cain</hi> ſhould kill his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, was no neceſſary truth before the thing was done; no more was it a neceſſary truth that <hi>Adam</hi> ſhould eat the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden fruit, before he had eaten it; and although it was a truth afterwards, yet no neceſſary truth: for no circumſtance of time can change the nature of things, as to make a contin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent truth to become neceſſary, or a neceſſary truth to become contingent. True it is that when a thing is done, it cannot be undone, (for a thing cannot be, and not be both at once) but it was not neceſſary that it ſhould be done, if it be a thing of contingent nature. What I now ſpeak or write, is neceſſary ſhould be thus ſpoken or written when it is once done: but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was done it was not neceſſary that I ſhould ſpeake or write in this manner, or ſpeak or writ at all, theſe being acts of freedom and liberty: ſo it is in all actions of the like nature, in all contingent actions.</p>
               <p>Thus we ſee that Gods determination and decree doth no whit infringe or obſtruct the liberty of mans will, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not withſtanding ſuch decree, man is no whit leſſe blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy, nor God at all faulty in the evill which man doth.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Object.</label> A third objection which may be raiſed from what hath been delivered is, that God hath been ſaid to be an accidentall cauſe of ſin, if ſo, then the ſinfull actions of men fall out beſides his ſcope and intent: for that is ſaid to be an effect by accident, <hi>quando aliquid p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aeter efficientis ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>pum accidit,</hi> when ſome event happens beſides the intent of the efficient: Now how can God will or decree ſinne, if it fals out beſides his ſcope and intents?</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſw.</label> To this doubt anſwer may be made by diſtinguiſhing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>intentio operis &amp; operantis,</hi> the intention of worke and the workeman: Sin is beſides the ſcope of the worke which God doth, but not beſides his owne intent who is the agent and workeman. When he decrees ſin ſhall be, he intends it ſhall be by ſuch wayes and meanes, by which acts and workes (ſo far as he works in it) as in themſelues and their own nature tend onely to good, and are meer accidentall cauſes of the evill
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:118412:25"/> which man does. The Law, and word of God, his mercies, judgements and all his dealing with men, in their owne nature tend to this end, namely, to make men better, nor worſe; and if they be made worſe by them, it is <hi>propter ſcopum,</hi> beſides the ſcope and intent whereto theſe things in their owne nature tend. The Goſpel in it ſelfe tends to life, when therefore it is the ſavour of death, it is beſides the proper ſcope intent and of the Goſpel: but though it beſides the intent of the Goſpel to be the ſavour of death, it is not beſides Gods intent, for he both knows and intends in what effect the Goſpell ſhall have: otherwiſe he ſhould be defective in his wiſedome and provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence: beſides what power the Goſpel hath to produce an ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect either way, it receives from him. Hence it is aid to be the <hi>power of God unto ſalvation,</hi> Rom. 1.16. the powerfull inſtrument which God uſeth to bring men ſalvation, which power he puts into it: and ſo likewiſe when he workes the other way it is power alſo. The Lord bids the Prophet <hi>Go make the hearts of this people fat, and make their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ares heavie, and ſhut their eyes, &amp;c,</hi> Iſa. 6.10. and how ſhould he do this? namely, by preaching the word unto them; by which it appeares, that ſometimes the word doth harden mens hearts, cloſe their ears and ſhut their eyes; and that God intends it ſhould do ſo, and ſends it for this very purpoſe; yet the word in owne nature tends to ſoften their hearts, to open their eares, and eyes, to make them ſee and heare better; ſo that the word here is onely an accidentall cauſe (it being beſide the ſcope and intent of the word to har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den:) yet this is not beſides Gods intent, who in all his acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and in the uſe of ſuch inſtruments as are imployed in them propounds to himſelfe a moſt ſure and certaine end. By all which appeares as the ſecret and juſt judgement of God, ſo his infinite wiſedome and skill, who can worke out his owne ends by ſuch meanes, as in their owne nature do tend a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary way.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:118412:25"/>
               <head>CHAP. X. Shewing ſome uſefull concluſions which do neceſſarily follow from what hath been ſpoken of this Subject.</head>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Conclu.</hi> 1.</label> IF God ſo ordereth things, that in all the ſins which are committed by men though he hath a ſecret working hand, yet he workes in a moſt juſt and holy manner, and doth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but what is right and good:</p>
               <p>Hence it followes, that in all the ſin which is committed, in all the evill which is done, either by our ſelves or others we lay all the blame on our ſelves or them, not imputing the leaſt miſcarriage on God, not ſo much as in our thoughts, <hi>He is juſt in al his wayes, and holy in all his workes;</hi> what ever he doth is well done, be the inſtruments never ſo bad by whom it is done.</p>
               <p>In all the evill that befals us, we have no juſt reaſon at all to repine and murmur, to be impatient or diſcontent; for all his dealings with us, whether by his word or his workes, his mercies or his judgements, do in themſelves tend to good: when therefore any evill comes we muſt take heed we do not charge <hi>God</hi> fooliſhly, <hi>Iob.</hi> 1.22. but remember that we have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured theſe things to our ſelves (as the Prophet tels the people, <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.17.) Sin is the ſeed of ſorrow: all the evill of ſuffering ariſeth from the evill of ſinning, and this ariſeth onely from our ſelves: yea, though ſometimes we ſuffer many evils alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether unjuſtly as they proceed from men, yet as they come from. God (who guides all the actions of men) they are done moſt holily, wiſely and juſtly. Thus <hi>Daniel</hi> acknowledgeth in regard of himſelfe and his people, <hi>O Lord, righteouſneſſe belongs to thee, open ſhame to us,</hi> Dan. 9.6. <hi>Thou art juſt in all that is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>one upon us</hi> (ſaith Nehemiah) <hi>for thou haſt done right, but we have done wickedly,</hi> cap. 9. laſt. <hi>Let God be true and every man a lyar</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.4.) So let God be juſt and holy, and every man ſinfull, wicked, and wretched abundantly worthy of all the evill which comes upon him.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Conclu.</hi> 2.</label> Hence it follows, that we ought with all reverence to admire
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:118412:26"/> and to adore the infinite wiſedome, juſtice and power of God, that is able to worke in the moſt blame worthie actions of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full men, and yet himſelfe remaine altogether blameleſſe: that is able to bring about the beſt ends by the worſt meanes: that in many great works which have been done in the world, hath wrought out ſuch ends, as have been altogether different, yea, ſometimes contrary to the ſcope and intent of thoſe who have been the principall actors and agents in them. Little did <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſephs</hi> brethren thinke that when they ſold their brother for a ſlave, this ſhould be the meanes of making him the greateſt mam in all the Land of <hi>Egypt</hi> next to <hi>Pharaoh.</hi> Little did <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> thinke that when out of his hate and indignation againſt <hi>Mordecai,</hi> he gate a decree of deſtroying all the Jewes in the Kings Dominion in one day, that this ſhould be a meanes and occaſion of making them have a hand againſt their adverſaries and of procuring liberty to deſtroy them? yea, of bringing himſelfe to the Gallowes, <hi>Heſt.</hi> 8.11.7.10.</p>
               <p>Little did the Jewes thinke that their envie and hatred againſt Chriſt ſhould be an occaſion of redemption of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, that when they ſpit upon him, buffeted him, beat him with rods, crowned him with thornes, cauſed him to ſuffer the ſhamefull and accurſed death of the Croſſe, that this ſhould be a meanes of his greater advancement and exaltation: yet the Scripture ſaith, that becauſe <hi>he made himſelfe of no reputation, and humbled himſelfe to the death of the Croſſe, therefore God highly exalted him, and gave him a name above every man,</hi> Phil. 2.8. what reaſon therefore have we in way of admiration to cry out with the Apoſtle, <hi>Oh the depth of the riches both of the wiſedome and ounſell of God, unſearchable are his judgements and his wayes paſt fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding out,</hi> Rom. 11.33.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>
                     <hi>Conclu.</hi> 3.</label> Thirdly, hence it follows, that we ought to acknowledge with all thankefulneſſe that infinite goodneſſe of God, which doth not ſuffer us to goe on in a courſe of ſinning, eſpecially in ſuch a ſort as would ruine our ſoules, and drive us to deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: for if he ſhould it would be in vaine for us to complaine againſt him; he would eaſily acquit himſelfe and juſtifie his owne proceedings: he would be <hi>juſtified in his words, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come when he is judged</hi> (as the Apoſtle ſpeakes, <hi>Ro.</hi> 3.4.) he would
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:118412:26"/> eaſily convince us, that in all the evill which we have done, or ſhall ſuffer, the juſt blame lyes upon our, owne heads, and our deſtruction is of our ſelves: he would cauſe our mouthes to be ſtopped, and make us (as all the world) to <hi>be found culpable before him,</hi> Rom. 3.10, If he ſhould enter into judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with us, we ſhould not be able to anſwer one of a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand: what a mercy is it that he doth not ſuffer us to fall into ſin ſo frequently, and in ſo fowle a manner as we are ready to doe, eſpecially that he doth not charge our ſins upon us. What reaſon have we to ſay with the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Praiſe thou the Lord, O my ſoule, and all that is within me praiſe his holy name, who forgiveth all thine iniquities, and healeth all thine infirmities, who doth not deale with us after our ſins, nor reward us after our iniquities; but as high as the heaven is above the earth, ſuch is his mercy towards us; as far as the Eaſt is from the West, ſo far he doth remove our ſins from us,</hi> Pſalm. 103.1,3,10,11,12. to him alone be all glory now and ever.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
